Uh, welcome everybody. I'm going to call
the
Andover Planning and Zoning June 16th
meeting to order
and
we're going to do the roll call. Present
Dan Larson.
I think William Hutchinson absent. Scott
Pan called out and so we need to seat an
alternate.
Um
Marie, would you be willing to get
seated as alternate today?
>> Is Kevin here?
>> Uh or Kevin seated last time. He might
be online.
>> No, there's only those four that just
there's only those three.
>> Yeah, I'm fine.
>> Okay, thank you. You're welcome.
>> Moving on to item three. We're going to
add the agenda under new business add a
B
and we've received a special permit
application. So, we're adding that for
new business item B.
All right. Public speak.
>> I I was surprised since there was no
item on the agenda for filling the alert
position.
Thanks.
>> It's going to be posted this Friday and
the Friday after.
>> Okay.
>> For I think have to be in by July.
>> So,
>> thank you.
>> It's on the website, but I haven't paid
close attention to whether or not it's
been print media. So, apparently didn't.
>> No, I didn't get in the timeline. I
didn't get it in and so it has to go
this week.
Uh, public speak. Anything that's not on
the agenda?
>> Hearing none. Moving on. All right. Item
five, old business. Uh, we're starting
off with
Scott Electric Press.
>> All right. Um, I send I believe email.
>> I should just show you this over here.
>> All right. that roll
out post
>> what I share with you.
>> Jonathan, you let me share.
>> Uh, yeah, sure.
I think uh we've seen this, right?
>> Go for it.
>> All right. So, I'm assuming everyone in
here has driven past us a bunch of times
on six. Uh we're enter I've found the
construction that we've decided to go
ahead with on this expansion project.
We're looking to add about 11,000 square
feet to our current footprint. Um, we
proposed this addition in this floor
plan layout that you see right here. And
essentially just looking to kind of keep
the straight line from the latest
edition all the way down to the uh end
of the parking lot, but we would like to
keep the little slight rumbout from the
restaurant.
This would bring our total footprint we
believe to 34,000 square feet probably.
>> So the restaurant that was there that
front that def facade that's going to
stay the way it is.
>> It's going to be
>> it's going to be torn down, but we want
to keep that footprint.
>> We're going to keep the same footprint.
>> We're not coming closer to the road.
>> No, just keeping that same footprint.
We'd like to keep that front for like a
break room for our employees.
>> Um Wayne, I I I don't believe this is
shared with everyone. I I can see the
the overhead projector on the screen,
but it's not shared on Zoom. Do you want
to try sharing your screen again?
>> Okay,
here.
I'm sorry.
>> Okay, here it comes. Thank you.
Yes, you'll see on the both edition
there's that slight bump out there. That
is part of the uh the restaurant of the
floor plan that we would like to keep in
our expansion project.
there.
So, my zoning only question for you guys
really was
u the to do with the parking mix that's
going to be in front. How far from the
edge of Route Six
is that do you think do you think is
this just an exceptional? Yeah, I have
this screenshot of
>> it's actually further away from West
there now.
>> So, if you look at that little floor
plan right there, you'll see in the
front of the uh current the old
restaurant that we actually have parking
already out in front of the building.
The parking will eventually go up along
the perimeter of the latest addition.
So, it'll the parking lot will be closer
to the building than it is now.
>> Okay. So, where you're parking now in
front of the the restaurant?
>> Yeah. That's no longer going to be
there. You're going to be along the
perimeter
of the building
>> on the of the latest edition.
>> The right hand side.
>> Yeah. Right here. This gray part right
here.
>> Well, this
over here.
>> Uh, no. But this is route six. So right
here is existent pavement that comes
around. So this is all going to go away.
So what's paved there is kind of being
pushed back and there's a lot that's in
over here right now. Correct.
>> Which is
>> that
>> that way that's all building,
>> right?
>> Yeah. So So we're we're a little further
away from
>> Route six than we we are now.
>> Okay. Correct.
We currently employ around 50 employees
and by doing this we believe we get up
to 75 to 80.
>> You have to um add on like you set there
you will
>> I I believe what they have there will
will work but we'll have to look at it.
I I think they have a 100% reserve
build. You do have to they right now
they have a pump within the proposed
addition. So that will just be moved out
>> and brought out. So
>> right
>> but that's something we we're talking
concept right not talking actual
>> correct. Yeah
>> this is going to change.
>> This is going to look different. This is
just like a highle idea as to you know
what we want to accomplish here in the
coming months. you will you'll likely
have to I don't know if it's the state
that actually or is it Eastern Islands
that does the
>> the for the septic
>> for the septic? Yeah.
>> Yeah. We'd have an engineer design it,
>> right?
>> And then and then it would go from
there,
>> right? So the study has to be done and
to be deter.
>> It's it's going to be almost certainly
uh local approval. Uh it would have to
it would have to kick up over 5,000
gallons a day
>> to have to deal with the state
>> and septic for industrial business type
buildings is pretty
>> Yeah. No, it's just it's just about
flow. It's just about what how much
what's the volume put into the ground.
>> Wayne, last time we were talking there
was a question came up about the
distance to the road.
>> Right. Right. Did uh we find anything in
the existing file or anything like that?
>> Um I believe there was an allowance in
the last edition from 2010 I believe was
66 ft or so from the road.
>> Yeah. So there's been like three three
different additions to this.
>> That's correct. Yeah. Um the
one of them was done with site plan
approval because it met all setbacks
and two were done with special permit
and in
I sent it to you guys uh section 23
something the commission has discretion
to reduce the setbacks for business and
industrial.
So, if they're not going any closer to
the street than what already exists, I
think they should be okay.
>> I don't disagree with that. I'm just
trying to figure out how the logic, you
know, got us there. It was a surprise to
me to hear that for the business zone,
it was 100 ft from the edge of the road,
right? as opposed to the center line
which is everybody else. I didn't know
if that's an error in regulations or
whatever. So I curious what you found
out looking back at that.
>> Yeah, I I I sent uh that section of
regulation to the commission. remember
that
allowed by special permit
for the reduction in that
100 ft setback.
So that's how I believe that the
um
that's how I believe that that the uh
restaurant was placed closer than 100 ft
to the road.
And
um there went another addition that
ended up being closer than 100 ft to the
road that was approved.
This addition isn't going any closer to
a road than what's already there
as I can tell.
>> No, it's not.
What you're looking at is essentially
what it's going to be, right?
So from my perspective, I think this
>> this is going to square it all off.
>> This proposal
um can be supported by existing
regulations.
What's that?
>> Yes. The only other thing going through
my mind is there probably a requirement,
you know, for some
storm water remediation because the
addition that's going into it.
Well, they have in the back corner that
you can see they have an existing um
retention basin, sedimentation basin. So
I mean we may have to increase the size
of
>> Yeah.
>> And then that goes down into the hot
bird right
>> so we would just need to see those
calculations.
>> Yeah. I mean that's something for the
civil engineer to think about.
>> Yeah. You're going to be adding
impervious surface. So you'll have to do
something in an industrial business zone
to handle any additional storm water.
>> So you said this is a concept that we
hoping to break ground
>> probably spring.
>> Spring of next year. Yeah. We just last
week now it's been going on for a few
months now. But last week we just got
the financial appro approval from our
owner to go ahead with it and we gave
Zlotnik the green light to start going
ahead and finding a uh some design team
to move forward. So hopefully this time
next year there's some metal frames
going up and we're in there by next fall
or so.
And
here
just kind of an idea of what we're
looking for the front. Dress it up a
little bit. So it'll look much cleaner
on route six.
>> The existing building footprint was
>> It is really
>> Yeah. They just kept adding on um wide
variety of different 67,000 square foot
additions over the course of time. Yeah.
>> And now we have more than enough work
and looking to bring on five more
employees here in the coming weeks.
Scale up to next year, be up to 80. So
we have a lot of exciting things going
on.
>> Um, your business hours currently are
just first shift. Just first shift.
>> First shift. Yeah. Uh 7 to 3:30. you
guys are anticipating a second shift and
whatever say 10 years down the line 5 10
5 years down the line and something we
might have to consider but not in the
immediate term at all.
>> Yeah, I was just noticing like we didn't
address lighting. I mean I know these
are specifics but these keep it in mind.
>> Yeah.
>> Uh under new constructions we have dark
sky compliant in our rights. So that's
just that in mind.
>> Yeah. Well, there's that light they put
up there at the intersection right in
front. That's temporary, right?
>> Oh, the traffic lights.
>> Yeah.
>> Well, I guess it was a dream that it
wouldn't be per
>> No, I know. I know. A while back, we
tried getting a piece of land uh bought
off from them to the there's the lot
adjacent to us
>> to use for uh parking, but uh it's under
forestry agreement, I believe, for the
next two years. So, the owner doesn't
want to sell.
All right.
Any
other discussion from the commission?
>> All right. Okay. So, so next step for
you guys at least from the zoning
perspective. Well, you do need you need
to go to wetlands first before you you
come to you go to zoning to zone. So um
you have to make the application to
inland
inland wetlands commission and you can
make the you can do the fill the forms
out at the same time but um they have to
approve this
or it has to be approved by in the lands
before zoning can act on the
application.
Sounds good. All right. Thank you guys.
Thank you guys.
All right. Moving on to
5B.
Thank you.
Evening chairman.
Miami is Peter Valley and I am president
CEO of design professionals incorporated
happens to be an 18 person
multi-disiplinary
practice to offices in South
retained by LK Holmes LLC of Mansfield
uh John Callahan secretary one of our
three clients uh to perform planning
uh civil engineering architecture and
land surveying services are associated
with the development they previously
presented to him in April uh
conceptually before we're involved.
Also with me tonight from design
professionals or VPI is Lauren Melo to
my right. He's a licensed professional
engineer in Connecticut and other
states. She's our director of operations
experienced civil site civil engineer uh
and she is also accredited uh with the
congress on new urbanism um which is at
the forefront of some of the stuff that
people are doing with respect to site
design.
our clients here. Uh well, we mentioned
Sean is here on Zoom is Gavin Duffy.
He's was on earlier. I think he's still
on
>> and not with us tonight. He's the last
few.
>> Oh, he's on too. Okay. He's zoomed in.
Okay. The four is also on the third of
the three.
Uh
so as they explained in in April, it's a
large site on the south side east of
Route 87. This can be signal signal uh
at the in the back of properties of
Columbia Town line
once known as Rosewood Acres, a
subdivision that was approved by expired
and and is therefore null void
designers.
So that's that's the fun. Uh we're here
to present to you our thoughts and
preliminary layout uh for the concept
layout for a uh mixed use development
um
that our clients are proposing uh and
they would like to develop it under the
and under Andover's mixed use floating
zone. That's sections 26 of your
regulations. Uh major components we talk
about only highlight those. Lauren's
going to get into much more detail than
I am, but um 110 multif family units uh
along with a commercial component with a
15,000 foot building up along six for a
visor retail or office or other uses. We
believe the uses are listed in the B
commercial zone are the limited uses. Uh
and also a 40,000 foot self storage
facility also along Route 6 but
accessible and by one of the new streets
that Martin will go over. Uh and that
uh may or may not require a zone the B
zone. It's a little bit gray area at my
reading of the regulations. I've been
doing this for 50 years attending
government and 40 since we started this
40 years ago, but it looks like we might
need a zone change for the underlying
zone Bzone for the commercial areas. If
not, if it's just what's allowed into
the B zone, even though we're the
underlying zone is residential for
almost every part of this little
exception. um and then facing northwest
corner on Route 6. Uh we may require a
zone change uh to the B zone first uh
along with some zoning text amendments
that I'll talk to the new about in a
minute.
Uh also the self storage use although
the definitions identify self storage in
your regulations uh they have a maximum
unit size for self storage units. Uh I
don't see this in the B zone and I don't
see it referenced anywhere in your uh
clothing zone either. So I would think
that that would need to be added to if
you were want to entertain the self
storage um to beef up our commercial
part of this component this um I would
think that would require a zoning text
amendment uh relatively simple process
to allow in the B zone. Therefore then I
think it's automatically allowed in a
floating zone if you were to prove that.
So,
>> so going back just a minute. Yeah.
>> I was trying to keep up with you when
you talked about the visit
>> and that would be to to because the
storage units that you've got there are
in the residential are not.
So, the entire property is in a
residential zone with the exception of a
tiny piece well under an acre. I don't
know the exact size we've done on the
survey, but um the northwest corner six.
So
>> where the uh where the stores are.
>> Yes. Yeah. Okay.
>> So
So what we're proposing is that u and
and this is my thought on reading it
interpreting the requisition and you
guys wrote it and I I didn't but I'm
reading it um as we're doing it for the
first time. I I'm suspecting that we
might make it clean when we go for a
zoning text for some things that don't
work for this development or it could be
better written in terms of getting
through the process with the commission.
Maybe not make it quite as long, but
we'll see. But at least it's crystal and
clear what we're doing. It's allowed by
the regulations. I I think it maybe
needs to have a zone change wherever
we're proposing commercial into the uh B
zone as the underlying zone. And then
there's overall you would approve the
overall development under the mixed
juice
uh flooding zone. It's an overlay zone.
So I that's my interpretation so far.
John I spoke to him briefly this
afternoon. He may agree with that or may
once we get into the week um I'm a
player. face planner a long time, but um
maybe we can uh uh work past that out
and see what they think and he can
confer with Mr. Guardian and other
commissioners how you may want to pursue
on that point.
>> Could I just jump in real quick?
>> Yeah.
>> So, uh for the record, John Gusowski,
town consulting planner. Um I there so
there's a couple of things that I think
need to happen. The the first is whether
or not this property needs reszoning,
which is to say a a designation change.
My read is not. Um, and I'm going to
read specifically from section 26.2,
which is applicability
um uh for the the uh mixeduse floating
zone. This says this floating zone may
be applied to any lot or assemblage of
lots with owner consent located in the
area designated business or industrial
on the Andover zoning map or which has
fee simple frontage on route six.
The recommended minimum size is three
acres. However, the commission may
consider smaller lots. So, there are two
criteria. either you're you're zoned
industrial or business or you have
frontage on Route 6. And whereas as you
know this you pointed out this is not
entirely zoned business or residential.
There's there's a split but the overall
property now that the subdivision has
been dissolved.
This entire property has direct fee
simple frontage on Route 6. And so by
virtue of that, it is my interpretation
it does not need a a change of zoning
district. It is eligible.
Um I'm I'm happy to hear arguments to
the contrary. It's at the top of the
next page, Wayne. Um
it's the first paragraph. Um
but but there are some uh text
amendments within section 26 the
mixeduse floating zone that will need to
be changed to enable this um
specifically
uh relative to runage on town roads
because there there will be a
subdivision necessary for this but I
think broadly within the master planned
concept it's possible I think you know
some text amendments will be helpful to
make this cleaner And then the second
element is right now there is a cap on
the blend between commercial square
footage and residential square footage
that uh we would need to amend in order
to enable something that is by far more
residential in terms of its square
footage. So we but as Peter said we can
hash out those specifics. Um but I think
to the first question about eligibility
as is I think it is eligible as is.
I I like what you're saying and I saw
that. I saw the French thing, but I
didn't want to go too liberal of a
determination on that or interpretation
of that, but I like that. So, if you're
of the opinion and the commission shares
that that we don't have to go for a zone
change to the underlying zone to B
because it's in the B zone, anything's
in the B zone, that's great. We still
need to do zoning text matter. Another
thing is it says reference is three
acres. That could either be the overall
track size before you can apply or it
means individual lots you create within
this zone the floating zone.
>> I I think it's I think it's the
assemblage of lots should be you know
the the lot or assemblage of lots to
land the zone
>> and then we'll discuss some of these
plots are under three acres that we're
going to be proposing. So that's
important. Um okay then that's very very
helpful. Thank you John. Um so we are
uh so the regulations call for a mix in
the end of them I noticed uh mix of
studio one and twobedroom units uh we
have been talking to our clients about
all two-bedroom units they have some
experience in the multif family in this
immediate area and they like the market
for two-bedroom units um they've had
some other unit styles that been slower.
They don't allow threebedroom units by
the way according to the regulations. So
um and they had some issues with those
renting them. Uh so we have discussed
the possibility of maybe adding some
studio and onebedroom units but it's the
question is your regulations right now
read a mix of studio one and two bedroom
units whereas right now we're only
thinking about two bedroom units
approximately 1200 square ft of size or
so. So the question is, are you okay
with doing all two bedroom or do you
want to adhere to have some more studios
in one bedroom? A lot of places, a lot
of communities in Connecticut have never
hit studio units. So we don't know what
the market is. There's not much in the
way of apartments in this town. So we
don't know exactly what it will be in
Andover, but the overall area of a sense
for that. So um there are a lot of
benefits to studio units. Um I've got
other clients who've done them. Uh and
also onebedroom units. Uh, but I I I
don't know what the thinking was for the
commission when you first went through
that exercise of adopting these
regulations. Do you truly want to see a
mix? We could do that, but the question
is how many how many unit studios and
one bedrooms would you require? And we
don't know what that is. Maybe that's
what we work with John on and get
feedback on a commission may very well
be the way to go. Um, so we can continue
this process. Well, unless anybody has a
strong feeling on that, we'll just move
on to some of the other items.
>> We have a question. Go ahead.
>> Um, I was going to ask you before you
mentioned that why you were you were
proposing entire nothing but two-bedroom
units. I would think it would be a
little bit easier for you to market dump
if there was some I don't have a
percentage in mind, but if there were
some onebedroom
or studio units, it just seems to make a
little more. But the population just
started down
>> from my perspective. I think if we're
doing this number of units, I think the
market
some studio one bedroom uh the question
is how much if it's not a large
requirement. They have an experience of
like doing this in this immediate market
within 10 miles or So they're concerned
about getting into a commitment for
units that may not rent uh in and over 6
and 87. So I guess maybe it's maybe it
comes down to discussion about what kind
of percentage you want or how many units
or if you want some if it's you know if
it's a relatively modest number
you know that we can certainly discuss
that but they they're comfortable with
two better units and I know in the
planning conservation development um
it's pretty strong you want to also um
as many communities around here we're an
aging population like to get some
families in here and I admire that you
also don't have the problems that some
communities around here have like where
our office is and where I live reside
where they have overcrowding schools and
they don't want they just built four of
them and they brand new ones and they're
overcrowded and they don't want to have
any children coming into town right now
because of the the overcrowding but
bringing kids into the community I I
like communities that have young
families and children and welcome them
and that's what I think you're trying to
achieve with the surveys you've done and
with the play concentration development.
So I think that's a great idea to do it.
So the two bedroom does that but uh the
onebedroom and the studios tend to take
tend to not accommodate children. So
that's one factor um looking back at
that. But you know you need every every
community in Connecticut needs
additional housing of all types.
So, I think this is a good starting
point and I think we can maybe get some
feedback. John can confer with you and
get some feedback on what you prefer,
what you'd like, what you're comfortable
with. Um, so that could be part of the U
zing text amendment.
>> And we've had a lot of discussions on
the commission in the last several years
and even more so recently about, you
know, what's affordable by definition.
Um, you know, seniors or people just
starting out. um from an affordability
point of view, people who want to stay
in town but want to downsize.
>> Um people who don't necessarily have
children, people who are, you know,
minimalist,
but I think for those reasons, I'd be
interested in
some percentage of it.
>> Okay.
>> Smaller than two bed.
>> Yeah. We had discussion the other day in
our office and so it's not new
discussion. So, we already know we we
didn't make any decisions and we wanted
to hear from you first and from John as
well and Wayne about what their thoughts
were on that. Um, but yeah, it's out
there right now. The regulations say
that if you want to change from that or
if you just want to say, yeah, we want
we don't need to have a large number of
studios in one. I wouldn't want to have
for example all studios or all one
bedroom. I can't be a big mistake. Um,
but having some in there may be prudent
and a good idea for the community and
because there's some single adults, kids
who get out of graduate from your high
school school system here, random and
stuff and they um may they can't afford
much other than maybe a onebedroom or or
a studio or even with someone else. So,
and that's what if they have a roommate,
which is what my kids did, they had a
roommate and they shared it even though
sometimes they're a stranger. Um my
daughter, you know, ran with another
young lady and they had a twobedroom.
They both had their own bedroom and
worked out in a shared kitchen area. So,
so um that's why two bedrooms work a lot
of times. Um they tend to always work.
Um but the cost is higher and there's
there are different markets. Yeah.
>> You also require them all to be two
stories, which is what they're thinking
of, twotory townhouse. But if we want to
do a studio or one bedroom, we start
getting unless you want to get into
stairs or a second and I've done those
developments in the last 10 years,
plenty of them where you walk up to the
second floor for a different unit and
then we were proposing and proposing a
garage with every unit attached garage
and it gets interesting when you get
into studios and one bedroom and some
are above others and can you fit in
another garage or not? Do they are are
the lower cost studio units? they have
their own garage or not. Those are those
are questions we need to address. But I
I think we can I think I think we'll be
able to accommodate a lot of your
concerns. In fact, in order to get
approval, we will. So, no question.
>> We we just we just kind of need to know
what kind of numbers you guys are
looking at. I mean, preferably leave the
studios out is what my preference would
be. Um, but to go down to the the
handful or so onebedrooms
>> and and what Peter was talking about, we
we had the discussion office a couple
days ago was to put those onebedrooms
kind of in a section by themselves so
that if there was a husband and wife who
had a child, they're not on the outsides
of a one bed. So we, you know, if if you
sat here and told me, "Hey, we need
seven one beds at a for you guys to move
forward with this project." We would
find a spot, well, like this one over
here or something, and those would all
be one bedrooms in that whole something
like that.
>> So in that case, they wouldn't be
dispersed throughout the room,
but they'd also one bedroom would be
you're not you're unlikely to have a
second floor. I would thank you. So, one
bedroom would likely be a ramp style
unit,
>> which is a different architectural
style.
>> There are other there's considerations
like that.
>> And did you say there's a garage
proposed for every single unit?
>> Yes.
>> Attached right there with a unit.
>> Yeah.
>> This is the original. I mean, we
obviously we just took this offline, but
that
>> architecture
>> looking to build.
>> All right.
>> Now, I'm not saying it's going to be the
exact same, but that's roughly what
we're looking to do.
>> Underneath there with your entry door,
two bedrooms upstairs,
>> and that's in that document presented in
April.
>> It'll be a bath and a half.
>> And so, if you go into studios also,
they're proposing a bath and a half. And
I like that idea of a bath and a half
for a two-bedroom unit. Um, if we go
down into a studio, I've never seen one
with more than one full bath. Yeah. When
you have to have a full bath, and I've
never seen one and a half baths for a
studio, but they probably exist. Um,
actually a real high-end house once it
was 5,000 square feet, but it's
different
on the coast. But, um,
and I'm sure they couldn't sell it to
anybody else after that, otherwise had a
beautiful view, whatever. But, um, yeah.
And in a onebedroom,
typically those one bedrooms are one
bath instead of one and a half. Since
you get two or more, I it's one and a
half or two or two and a half bathrooms.
So,
>> which is fine. It'll just be a slightly
different design the architect than what
we're going to be building in other
areas. That's why I I would prefer not
to have an architect do five, six
different designs because obviously that
gets very costly. So, if I can just do,
hey, these are all one bedrooms and
they're one bath and you got a row of
six, you got a row of seven, there you
go.
>> With a nice steep pitched roof, which is
what I think you encourage um a ranch
style one floor living for a building
like that could be very attractive. And
they're only talking to people,
architects, prospective architects who
do really nice work and they're
beautiful. So,
>> so are you on the commission when we
approve this session? No.
>> Okay. So,
I know the the original village no mixed
use commercial residential was the
intent was more like
>> uh single people that might be working
in the shops there, you know. So, this
is like a different application.
You know, the original intent of I think
15 or 20 years ago was a lot different
than it is now, too. Plus, the market's
changed. there's less brick and mortar
uh commercial property. So go ahead
say you so I don't think anybody here
maybe the average involved in that but
this the first go through a mixed huge
thing so you're you're giving it a hard
look. Yeah, they're coming up with good
questions. You know, whenever you write
the procedure and you never really used
it, you do the best you can. I thought
it was pretty good. But, uh, the, uh,
there's going to be a lot of things that
we're going to have to, you know, sort
out with you a little bit. If we have to
change it, you know, and Lauren and I
learned for 13 years and me for 50
years, 10 years in regulatory investing.
I've seen a lot of res and our firm has
done about a thousand residential
contracts that could be as little as an
addition house all the way up to a large
multif family development registry all
that stuff. So we we have a lot of
experience in there we'd like to share
with you as we go forward. Uh some other
things. Uh
yeah, in terms of uh the mixture, John
mentioned we may have to do a text
member regarding the mix. If we had
right now, if they're all 1,200T units,
we'd be and based on we have a self
storage 40,000 ft and a 15,000 foot
building, could be retail, could be
medical office, what have you. Um out
front six. Um and that's 55,000 ft of
commercial total. Uh if they're 100%
1,200 square foot twobedroom units would
be slightly over that ratio. You want
66% residential maximum and 33% uh
commercial minimum. Uh so it' be a
little bit worse that if we if we add in
some studios and one bedrooms the total
square footage drops
and for example if we did all 1100 foot
units we'd meet that threshold without a
zoning tax for that. So just food for
thought. So if we go into some studios
which are typically like 500 square feet
or whatever um somewhere in that range
or 450 500 600 ft per studio and one
bedrooms can be um you know a bit larger
than that but not much larger um they
don't need to be 800 ft but um still
those those we can we can reduce it. So
that alone may bring us to meet that
requirement without needing a zoning
text amendment for that because I've
seen zoning regulations like this where
you like to have a good ratio. You want
to have about a third commercial and 2/3
residential max. This is not not that
atypical for regulations that I've seen.
I remember from the last time you guys
were here um that this represents phase
one, but you have some other land here
that you were thinking about for for
later development. So, so what we ended
up doing was was was Lauren and Peter
got together and they actually moved, if
you look on the on the bottom here, this
this was in our original, we've got some
houses here now.
>> Yeah.
>> And they moved the storage units down
towards the loop six here so they can be
seen from group six.
>> So there would there would no longer be
a phase two.
>> Okay.
It's all one large savannah without any
land held in escrow, but they will have
to face the building to building for
financing reasons and marketability. You
can't you drop them all on the market
units or pay taxes on and building
permanent fees ahead of time before they
leave and they don't like
>> I like where you put them because where
where the original proposed was is it's
backing up uh Colombia.
>> Yeah. and like eight different
properties and they all have back
porches. They will be looking right on
the storage room. So, I think that was
smart to put them in the front just by
personal opinion.
>> Lauren did that.
>> Yeah, I tell you what, she she's really
talented and um she's running our whole
site design unit now studio at the
office. Um and it will show as she goes
into that. Um, so also, uh, oh, by the
way, so we're still talking about the
multif family would be sprinkler. Uh,
you're still talking about that.
>> We're going to have to sprinkle.
>> That's right.
with a tank in the basement and then a
>> well it's again I don't think if
>> these guys are going to care either way
more the fire marshall but
>> depending on on what we can do it will
either be one very large underground
tank
>> and that would feed all the sprinkler
structures we'd have to run pipe in the
ground to feed everything or it will be
tenants in the basement on separate
pumps which may just get way too costly
to
It'll be up to the fire
>> and like a lot of people we've been
doing which are owner occupied housing
and stuff. They're retaining ownership.
They're invested for the long haul. Um
they're they're coming in the whole
thing maintaining all that. Um question
um because we were talking about uh text
amendments and and stuff like that. So,
I have up here this 15,000 square foot
uh limitation on retail space
and you're proposing 40,000 square foot
of self storage.
>> I don't know if that's considered retail
space or not. Um now
even so that's uh it just seems to me
that um
I don't know if it it shouldn't be an
impediment if if the commission you know
is isable but but it seems to me that
that 40,000 square foot of of self
storage either should be reszone
business or something needs to be done
to the mixed use
um mixed use section to accommodate
that.
>> Well, it's not going to be one 40,000
square foot building or even three of
them. It's it's they're going to be
broken up. I mean, on on the
>> same the 15,000 square foot retail space
and and then you have some additional
space that is going to be commercial
commercial use. Let's put it that way.
>> Yeah. Yeah. And and I think that's the
intent of the regulation was to have
that third of the development square
footage to be commercial,
>> right? But it doesn't exactly that,
>> right?
And jobs.
>> I'm just saying it doesn't the
regulation has written I don't think
specifically addresses.
>> I agree.
>> So you think we need to address the
regulation on the square footage for the
commercial building?
Uh,
I think you need I I would like me I
would like to see words in there that
that address
commercial uses other than that retail
space.
>> Yeah. Yeah. Well, that's what we intend
to work with you and John on.
>> Right. Okay. That that's all I'm saying.
>> Yeah. No, that's good. Thank you. Um, so
because it's it does anything that's
allowed in a business zone or an
industrial zone is allowed in a mixeduse
zone, but neither one of those zones
talk about
um self storage.
>> Yeah. Right. Yeah, we definitely add
that somewhere into the regulations. You
have a great definition, but it's not
applied anywhere in the reg. I don't
even think it's in the industrial world.
>> No, it's not. Lauren knows. Uh and also
and Lauren could get into that. You
know, we're going to be having a wells
and septic system that makes it a lot
easier when we design development
projects on public water and public
sewer. There's no comparison. Lots of
issues come up. There are a lot of soils
testing allar. And also it kicks into
can we handle it with was it Eastern
Highlands? I think the uh the health
district here pretty sure we dealt with
them a lot and dealing with them where
we have to kick it up to the state D
which means we won't be seeing them
break ground for a long time because the
pro it's a long process get approval. So
if we that's why we want to split it up
into lots
one or two buildings for the residential
will be on a building lot and that's why
we we need to address that with wing and
and also with uh John about how we
address that and um whether or not it's
on a municipal street which would be
easy to carve out the lots or if it's on
a private street we have to have
regulations that allow for a private
street and then frontage on a private
street which is irregular but it's done.
So there are those issues here, but we
have to have them on separate lots so we
can have the maximum per lot not he
needing was 7500 or 5,000
>> 7500
>> 7500 gallons per day per day. Um as soon
as we kick into that over that we're at
D and she's been through a long process
on other projects. We don't want to go
there and he does Sean does not want to
go there. It'll be a lot of money, a lot
more money, a lot more expertise and and
and we don't know when we'll put a show
ground. It's too far in the future. Um
based on our collective experiences. Uh
let's see. Um
>> um if I might add, um we had our
economic development commission meeting
last night and that got brought up. Uh
there's at least one maybe two local
companies that can do those kinds of
systems if you need it. So just
>> system.
>> Yeah. for that that capacity. There's
there's newer techniques and newer uh
systems I mean that are more efficient.
>> The more prices you can get from people
down be obviously better.
>> Yeah.
>> People are at least very mobile next
time.
>> Well, this this was electric over here,
right?
>> Guys were here for electric.
>> I don't think they're electricians. Do
they build?
>> They're manufactured.
>> Yes. Electrical component manufactur.
But yeah, I'll have uh or you reach out
to the economic development chair Ela
Bark and she'll get you some names.
>> Yeah, they they want they want to have
list of vendors so they can get local
prices as much as possible and and and
and have reasonable price cost for the
overall development. Uh so we're
thinking about right now there would be
three planning and zoning commission
applications.
So the first one is definitely a zoning
text amendment that requires public
hearing by state law. And after we work
it out with Wayne and John and they
confer with you, we'll want to go
forward with that. Um hopefully they can
confer with you so we don't have to have
another informal because it's just
another month, another month, another
month. So we're hopeful that they can
work that out with you and get the
details we need for the zoning text
amendment we would be submitting. Uh so
that's one of them. and it may be a
zoning application to the Bzone part of
it, but John is telling us he doesn't
think we need to do that. So, if that is
indeed the case, then we want to do
that. We do it concurrently. So, that's
the first application. Second
application before you would be uh for
the zone change itself to the floating
zone uh and also for the master plan.
And most communities have very similar
regulations to a master plan. Master
plan is basically a preliminary
engineering plan. It's an advanced
concept plan. Uh it's not more detailed
than that. You don't want to get into
the heavy duty engineering learner staff
to do that um at great expense to our
clients before we change. So we try to
keep that down. But and and also in most
towns we don't go to the wetlands
commission for even though we're we're
as she explained to you we have one
proposal crossing of weapons uh to get
in for route 87 but um uh we don't go to
the weapons commission for an
application first because typically for
weapons commission requires an
engineered cycle uh and you won't be
level engineering to get all the details
you need for a wetlands application. So
we've typically done that after the zone
change in master plan or general plan or
advanced preliminary concept whatever
you're going to call it. We go to the
wetlands commission before you do
approve the engineered site plan which
you have in your regulations as a
special permit which also automatically
requires public hearing and we'll also
be doing under that at that level we'll
be doing the subdivision application.
It's not a resubdion as Lauren had
researched I guess the survey
department. Um it's because the the the
old subdivision's gone. We're not
creating more lots. We're not changing
the configures, whatever. We're starting
from fresh from scratch. There's been no
division of this property um other than
maybe one to first cut since the
effective date of subdivision law and
regulations in town of Andover. So um so
we see three that stand all required
public hearings. First one being uh the
zoning text amendment hostile zone
change to be zoned which may be ruled
out. We hope it is. Uh second one is the
uh the uh master plan concept uh and the
zone zoning uh map change. Uh and that
is for the flooding zone to be applied
to the property with the overall layout
you've approved and understanding what
we're doing without super detail
everything in details because they've
been engineered and stuff like that. Uh
and then the third one would be the site
engineered site plan with special permit
as your regulations to read right now.
If you want it toain remain a special
permit has been public hearing by state
law. If you decide again just enter your
site plan because you've already seen
the layout
multiple times before that you've
already liked it. You've approved it uh
with the master plan and zone change
application. So the question is do you
need a special permit as well? Um it's
just one a third public hearing, a third
night. Um it extends it all out to meet
once a month. Yeah. So we're talking
about the long process for them get
through wetlands and planning and zoning
um already. And then after that we have
um because we're over 100 multif family
units, we automatically we'll have to go
to the state office of office of state
traffic administration which is DOT um
for a state traffic permit. Uh and that
will take within four to five months
minimum after our engineers traffic
engineers not our office another office
has more expertise in that um who will
be um or really adept at that and
that'll take them once they submit it's
probably after we get our engineered
site approval maybe before that maybe
after master plan but I think
engineering site that's another four to
five months and possibly concurrent with
that probably concurrent with that will
be the DP
permit which is uh I call it storm water
discharge firm weather but there is
storm water pollution prevention plan um
uh anyways it's it's got one title on
that but that's because it's over 20
acres of disturbance of the site uh it's
a big site large site is will get into
um that's about 4 and a half months
process probably for us to do the u
storm application for them uh DP
application then give it to a third
party review another engineering furnace
to review it and That's like a month and
a half minimum. And then we submit and
it's about 90 days because it's over 20
acres. Is that correct? Is a 90-day
process. Normally 60, but with these pig
application. So that' be so so we're
talking another 4 and a half months. So
about same time frame as a step. Plus it
could be even longer than that. Um and
there are other steps involved. We need
to uh look at it. Does state um historic
preservation office require an
archaeological study? Um we can't submit
to the EP without knowing that. Um, so
there are other consultants involved. So
it's a it's a long process and we want
to get going on that. Um, this site
could be the uh this property could be
the highest taxpayer in town handover.
Um, I think the highest right now is uh
ever source because of lines you run
through. I don't think they have any
major substations here. Um, well I'm
pretty sure they don't. Uh, because I
saw their number just AI this afternoon
looking at it said the highest top
taxpayers in town. um it doesn't sound
like there's enough to justify that they
are covering a big substation. So um
this this probably will be one of the
top one, two or three taxpayers in town.
So I think it's good. And also a lot of
people don't take into consideration you
get the motor vehicle taxes for one or
two cars per household. You'll also get
the um you get the real property taxes,
you only get personal property taxes for
the commercial. Um it's the inside
elements of of building
whatever you have in there equipment for
an office what have you retail uh and
then also the building permit fees for
something this large sorry and he knows
that he pays them all the time but Sean
and and Gavin and and Leslie um that's a
big number and a lot of people don't
consider economic development
commissioning talking about that but I
do a lot of projects and they it's a big
number for the building permit fees so
much per thousand
um value of the work and it's a big
number also. So that's a benefit to um
significantly to the town. It's a res
it's a revenue source for the town. Um
uh we report on the plan conservation
development um you already know you've
seen it but it really supports this type
of development um wholeheartedly and has
other reasons we said I'm not going to
get into a lot of details but the master
plan the plan conservation development
is a great guide for land use and I
think it's consistent what we're
proposing here is very right on the
money for that and and I think it's a
great location for it in Andover there
are a lot of locations where it could do
something like this and this is one of
them. A lot of challenges with getting
septic systems to work and wells and
stuff we code but um it certainly looks
as doable. So I'd like to do without me
talking any further like turn it over to
Lauren because she's the one who laid
this thing out beautifully in
consultation with Sean and his partners
and myself and even our landscape
architect. So um why don't we just turn
it over her so she can explain what she
came up with and why and how.
>> Thank you Peter. Um, for the record, I'm
Lauren Melo, registered or licensed
professional engineer in the state of
Connecticut. Um, so Peter talked a lot
about um, text amendments and the um,
plan of development for Andover
um, similar conceptual um, and
preliminary engineering that we did for
this. Um, so the site which is outlined
in a thick red outline that holds 56.5
acres. Um the property breakdown you see
is a lot different than you saw in April
where it had 10 lots and they were all
like single family units on that old map
that it's subdivision map. Um right now
we're proposing 16 individual properties
not including what we'd call public
rightway that we can discuss with you
tonight. Um and those are separated by
the more the thinner red lines internal
to the property. Um two of those like
Peter mentioned are for business and
commercial use. the remaining 14 of them
will take beyond the residential. Um
it's important to note there's
significant grade change. It's about 200
ft from the southern um area of the site
down to route six. So we're looking at a
lot of um rate change.
Um on the plan green areas are shown for
designated open space um in recreation
areas. Um it's they were really
intentionally placed in areas that we
think will be slightly flatter that
people can gather. You can have like a
playground or some kind of gathering
space for people. Um the green clouded
line would be um the tree limits for the
site. As you know the whole site is
currently wooded. So that would be the
clearing limits. Um we'll try to
existing trees as much as possible. We
want to limit breaking as much as we
possibly can.
Um the gray area is of course the
roadways. Brown areas are the buildings.
Um blue shaded areas are for storm water
management. I'll get into that a little
bit more later. Uh the small blue
circles, little blue dots are wells um
that were strategically placed to avoid
other utilities um with setbacks to
property lines and buildings and under
drains that we would have to consider.
Um there's a couple really thin, hard to
see rectangles on this plan. Those would
be the septic fields. There's one septic
field per um lot with exception of the
um the storage uh property, the storage
building property lot because there's no
um there will be no septic and no water
proposed for that.
Um and then finally um the thin black
lines you might see are conceptual
retaining walls wherever we think
retaining walls might be.
Um, all right. For roadways, traffic
circulation and pedestrian access, we
know that was important to you in April,
especially concerning um emergency
vehicle um access and uh public school
bus transportation. Um I would also add
I'm sure mail delivery services and
delivery services are important too. Um
we would suggest a 20 foot maximum
roadway width um to com comfortably
accommodate all those vehicles. The
subdivision regulations currently say
30. Um, but we find that doors
appropriate, especially in a residential
area to really slow down traffic.
Um, however, we're also trying on this
plan or we considered um a 6ft
designated lane on that roadway that
would be dedicated just to walkers and
to bikers and any kind of pedestrian um
living in the area. You can stripe that
off. You can narrow the roadways with
striping. Um, but personally, I live in
a subdivision. The roadways are 30 ft
wide. We have sidewalks and no loop
system because they're hard to maintain,
especially with the very many streets.
Um, so we're proposing all that walking
space really to be on the roadway for
less maintenance for either the town or
for um the property owner.
Um the roadways we'd like you to
consider um making them town roads um
mainly because you have more control
over um maintenance plowing at the width
that we just talked about. We can always
discuss that you have more control over
what the actual design will be. Um and
you really have the final say in how
they're taken care of. Plus, with all
these properties going in, um, one goal
is to attract families um to help that
um that uh plan of development. And of
course, there'll be a lot of uh kids.
There'll be multiple school bus stops
throughout this um because there's a
considerable amount of roadway. There's
over 6,500 linear feet of roadway here.
Um and on the plan right now we would be
within 6.7 acres of um you'd say public
rideway or it could be as Peter
discussed earlier private roadway um
area.
Um moving on to the connections. So we
know that that's very important
especially on Route 6. Um we're showing
only one um entrance and exit off of
Route 6 and that is by lot one. Um and
that will encourage um access to that
lot to that business development. Um
that is about 1,200 ft from the Route
687 traffic light. There's there'll be
plenty of sight lines. Um and we'll have
to get the traffic engineer to look at
it later on in the design. Um though we
feel like it's um enough distance to
avoid any kind of uh traffic indications
there.
Um the second main connection is on 87.
That's on the south part the bottom of
the page. That will require wetlands
crossing. You can see that wetland line
with the um the thin line with like the
little flags on it. There's a wetland
scientist out there now flagging. Um and
it's preliminary results are showing
that the town uh math wetlands which are
what these are based off of are
relatively correct. Um so we're not
expecting major changes to uh wetlands
based on his analysis and his findings
um in that intersection. So I'm sorry
going back to the wetlands crossing
that'll either be in a form of a bridge
gold crossing um there will be template
impacts the wetlands in that area for
that.
Um and that intersection is 2600 uh feet
from the route 67 track. So it's well
distributed. Um, and then finally, we're
proposing a third connection to the Lyn
Homes Corner. Um, that's at the top of
the screen. There's currently a 30 sack
there. Um, Wayne Wayne and I spoke about
this a couple weeks ago. Um, and we
encourage us looking at this just for
another uh way out of the development.
We're currently showing the only
connection through the uh the roadway
network. There's no direct connection
between the lot one and that road. only
to discourage any kind of delivery like
large delivery trucks, tractor trailers
or box trucks exiting that area because
there are a couple residential
properties on that corner. Um, but if
you wanted a different design, um, it
would it could be accommodated there,
but there was a be something that we
discuss.
>> I just suggested you think about it.
>> Yeah. Yeah.
>> No, it was a great suggestion. And on
the grids work really well for that uh
connection down there
>> only because
it would make
egress easier
at the traffic light.
>> Yeah, absolutely.
>> But things may change and ultimately
it's the commission's wishes that you
you have to
>> follow.
Yeah. So that needs to change. We can
accommodate that too. We can make it
loop. We can also we like to avoid golds
just because they take up so much area
for the um
>> the fire truck to maneuver to 100 foot
diameter or just pavement.
>> Um so we probably connect that roadway
back up either to the north or loop it
around itself or do something different
with those two buildings on um lot two
and then lot 16 that we're showing. Um
but back to Lyn Homes Square that is
where Lynh Homes connects to 87 that's
400 feet from the um pathway to 87 and6.
>> Yeah.
>> How many miles of roadway did you say
the development?
>> We have 6,500. So it's a little over a
mile.
>> Yeah.
>> That's a lot of money.
>> Well, I guess that would be my next
question. There you go. Do you build the
road and then maintain it by the Dallas
>> by contractors? If you have public water
and public sewer, the whole enchilada,
all the utilities in more urbanized
community, they're they're quoting off,
to $1,200 running foot to build. In this
case, without that
700,
maybe $700 running foot to build a road
without sewer and water. I'm guessing
without swing mark to build the road
$4 a square foot
what $2 something dollar square feet.
>> Yeah.
Yeah.
>> Lauren, can you the width of the road
you you were
uh planning for a 24 foot wide road?
We'd like to um for the commission and
for John you commissioner 24 ft wide for
the vehicular terminal paths. Yeah.
>> The six foot lane for pedestrian bikes
whatever is
uh something that that in your mind is
optional.
>> Optional. It's really it would be really
great uh connect connectivity between
the entire site. um you know that the
residents are going to be walking.
>> Would that be pave or gravel lane? It
looked like the street just pavement
markings on it. Y
>> okay. So you would there'll be a 30 foot
wide road with with a 6 foot wide like
pedestrian lane
>> and all over the place. They're taking
big wide streets and then they're
creating multimodal pathways for
bicycles for people to walk and all
stuff all over. It slows down traffic a
bit too. So you narrow them down the
street. The traffic speeds go down and
there's also a safe area where you have
six feet so people can walk up rest and
not be in the street. And and a typical
4ft sidewalk doesn't really work for a
lot of things. Bicycles um
>> strollers,
>> strollers um you know three people
walking together um side by side. Um
whereas with six feet we find that to
work very well.
>> But there's no barrier, right? There's
no barrier between that and the the
street, but there would be markets.
>> I'm not a traffic engineer, but the way
this is presented here, it would not
present in an attractive shortcut
between 60 and 80s.
>> No,
>> correct. And the roadway right turn on
red.
>> The roadway was um deliberately laid out
to work with the grades because there's
such a grade change. Um it was really
the pathless uh least resistance. The
subdivision regulations call for a 15%
or less um slope on the road here.
>> 15% is pretty steep.
>> It's very steep. It's very very steep.
The maximum we have here based on um
available LAR, which is a little iffy,
um is about 12%. The worst% steep.
>> It's very steep, but it's a short
section.
>> It's a short section. It's right around
the curb on lot 10 between lot 10 and
lot
>> nine
>> the skiers who live there.
>> Yeah. Yeah. Um so we did
>> we did look to minimize the roadway
slopes. Um other than that it'll max out
around 8%. Besides that in the 12% area
it's around 8%. Um there's several areas
of uh 5% everything in front of the
buildings. um we just assumed was very
flat. Um so you'll have like that long
stretch like right in the um middle of
the screen right there. Like that whole
stretch is very you can walk that and
you probably wouldn't be able to tell
there's pre change. Um so it and it the
scale is 100 one one to 100. So it's
deceiving. Um but again there will be
sections of steep life. Um it's
unemployable
>> and that'll be all planned by Lauren
once she and her staff have the uh
survey to all done
survey graves. Yeah.
>> And then we can refund.
>> Have you have you worked into the plan
um snow storage
>> a little bit? Um for lot with the
storage built units we definitely did.
Um so there's like a little bit more
pavement on the end. Um, our land of
architect actually uh was in snow
removal for a short amount of time. So,
she
operated the truck, so she recommended
having a large area. They just push snow
off in in that um section. On lot one,
you can see like there's that big white
area kind of in the south of the lot one
corner. You can pile snow there. That uh
blue rectangle would be underground
detention um on top of a problem. And
then for interior state really any of
the open space areas um could be
temporary snow storage at some point. Um
>> the the reason why I'm asking is the
concern about um the walkability.
Um, I could definitely
imagine that the the road uh the the
clouds come by, it just piles up where
that walk where that walking space is
>> and then the kids have a known trying to
get to each other. They're they're
walking in the street.
>> That that should be a rare occurrence.
They should be plowing the full 30 ft
and pushing it off to the sides. So, um,
uh, as soon as they get to a break in
the driveways and stuff. So, I I think
that should be a problem with, as we all
know, we live in New England. Sometimes
we get a 30-inch snowstorm and it
surprises us. And then it's a problem
for every site. What do you do with
accumulated snow? It's not designed for
a 30in snowstorm or a 24 in for that
matter. In fact, the equipment can't
even move through it. You got to bring
in front and loader. So that that's
special circumstance, but there are lots
of areas for you to push snow off of the
roadway and off the multimodal pathway
as part of that 30 ft.
>> Yep.
>> Width.
>> Yep. Any anywhere you really don't see
green space. Um I shouldn't say any
area, but a lot of the area would be um
steep slopes. So like 5 to1, 31, and you
can push snow down there and it can be
out of the way. Um open space
requirements is a 15% or less slope in
those areas. So we we show the green
areas um wherever we can where we feel
like we can flatten it out a little bit.
So the white areas um there's
opportunity for
>> and there's a lot of road for that
driveway.
>> Lots of the the open space in the the
center. Yeah.
>> Um it looks like I can't see it very
well. It looks like there's some
topology there. Is it are you going to
be flattening that out? So
>> So that's a great question. Um, on the
original mapping, um, it's kind of hard
to see if there's like this, uh, thin
dotted line in that green area if it's
conference.
>> And we need to do a little more
research, especially with our survey
department, to really understand what
that is, if it's actually in place, um,
if it needs to be m um, maintained and
untouched.
um if it it if it is okay to develop in
there. Um we'd recommend putting some
type of storm water detention and
management feature in there. There's a
low spot. Um I believe when we were
talking with Sean um Leslie Gab at one
point they were saying that it was an
old gravel pit. Um so it is a depression
in the very long sloping area that is
screaming for storm water management. Um
so you can have a beautiful open space
area with walking trails and stuff in
there.
>> Can't tell she's a sibling.
Um, so yeah, but right now we're leaving
it as green space just to reserve that
area in case we can't currently wooded.
>> It's all wooded. Yeah. Yeah.
>> Right.
>> So that may it may have been proposed
part of the subdivision.
>> Right.
>> And then maybe said hey I put an ement
there all stuff
>> and an easement doesn't exist is my
understanding unless it's been recorded.
Uh and uh you know it's usually indeed
for that purpose without just because
it's not a map doesn't mean it's needed.
I think this space for the space he was
giving wasn't he giving land John
>> with the subdivision typically that
would be like a dedicated area that's
converted to open space
that that would have been a requirement
back for that back
>> it's still a requirement for a
subdivision either open space or fee in
lie of open space we have we have plenty
of time for open space
>> I'm sorry did did Wayne just answer the
question or or was there a separate
question for me?
>> I think I answered the question about
>> Okay. Yeah. Subdivision.
>> Yeah.
>> All right. Great. Um, moving away from
the roadway and just like focusing a
little bit on the lots. Um, lot one
shows a 15,000 square foot um, building,
which is the maximum currently allowed
into the business zone, which we spoke
about earlier. Um, you can have multiple
tenants in there or it can be a single
use like a medical office or something
like that. Um, it's yeah, lot one
next.
>> It's a commercial building.
>> Commercial building. It's that big table
away from the 90,000 square feet.
That's the loft size. That's confusing.
Yeah. Yeah.
>> It just happened to be it just
>> over.
>> I didn't place that. Um
um so what you can see on the screen,
you can also envision that to be a
grocery store. There's a space for a
loading area. Um we're showing 78
parking spaces which is greater than um
Angelber's regulations which allow for I
believe it's uh two to five spaces for
small commercial centers. Um and right
now um we're at 78 which is three over
the the five limit. Um hitting the
maximum would have been 75. So we're
three three spaces extra. And then
you'll notice all the parking's behind
um the building um as per the
regulations.
Um we talked a lot about the storage
units earlier. Um but I just wanted to
touch upon the parking really quickly.
Um there's four parking spaces proposed.
Um and like we said earlier like the
text amendments to really better define
what uh uh self storage looks like and
what's allowed um is kind of needed. uh
four kind of typical three to four for
other towns in the area. So we show
that. We also showed dumpster locations
on both sites and accounted for uh
garbage truck removal and um garbage
truck maneuvering and refu uh removal um
for that.
Um and then lot one's about 2.1 acres
and lot three is 4.9 acres um in total.
Um and then for the residential
buildings um that's on the remaining of
14 lots. It totals 41.1 acres. Um the
lots are anywhere between 1 to 5 and 1/2
acres each and that's really dependent
on the spatial requirements for
utilities and what's available in the
area um landwise for those buildings and
lots.
Each building contains six to eight
units. Um, and basements are being
considered. Um, and then finally, we tal
we spoke about each of them having a
garage, but each wall have a 25 foot
long ride. Um, so you'll have that extra
parking space in front of their garage.
Um, architecture is still being
discussed. Um, um, Sean, Gavin, and
Leslie have been talking a few
architects and are getting one on board
soon. Um, so everything may change. Um,
but we've also discussed together walk
out basement and um using the buildings
as retaining walls or retaining back
some of the grade in some areas to
really working with the grade. Um, and
then finally, there are 10 really small
um parking lots like scattered
throughout the development. You'll
notice they're in like near near open
space areas or between units and that's
for consideration of like visitors.
Yeah, visitor lots.
Um, and there's 55 spaces total for
that. Um,
okay. So, then just talking a little bit
more about grading the topography. Um,
our goal, um, is to minimize earthwork
like we mentioned before, but also
retaining walls. Like, we want to grade
the site out. We don't want massive
retaining walls and just any wall um, in
your backyard. Um, that's never a good
book.
>> And they're expensive.
>> They're expensive.
Um, and then we talked a lot about open
space, but we're also committed to
keeping um a lot of open space areas
with that less than 15% slope. Um, and
then my only other note on that we
talked about was the conservation ement
that we'll address
when we get more into survey.
Um, and then just to finish things up on
like the civil conceptual level, um, I
just want to talk about like storm water
utilities and environmental things. Um,
as I mentioned, the wetland scientist is
actively delineating the wetlands on
site now. He's finishing up this or next
week. Um, afterwards we'll do an A2
boundary survey along with uh T2 or
topography. It depends on where we are
on the site. T2 is a little more
detailed. T3 is a little less detailed.
So T2 will use in those areas that are
more sensitive like near the wetlands,
near Route 6, near 87, you know. Um
for storm water management, those are
the bigger blue areas you'll see on the
screen. Um
we are suggesting um that there are at
least two townmaintained or um property
owner maintain large detention basins.
ones right there in that green square.
Um that could also double as open space.
That pond there would manage all of the
storm water runoff from the roads, a
vast majority from the buildings because
it would all flow down there. Um we can
manage it in order to clean it, detain
it, slowly releasing it to the Route 6
um state system that's in that roadway.
Um the second one, we have a smaller one
a little bit down um as well. And then
of course we can do one in the open
space conservation easement if they can
flow too. Um we're envisioning those
doubling as the fire suppression ponds
for the bumper trucks when um they they
need water. There's ways designing those
basins so they don't infiltrate and they
hold water in their wet ponds. Um so we
can look into that.
Um
and then for lot one and lot two, the
commercial
um pieces, we'd like to handle the storm
water separately for those. Quite
honestly, it's because they're down
slope of everything, so the water is
already running that way. Um lot three
would be easy. You can do a a surface um
pond close to Route 6 before discharging
to the state system and that roadway.
And then lot one be subsurface. And you
can see that blue rectangle there. we
can put a subsurface uh um storm water
system in there.
Um and of course we're open to working
with Wayne and with John on um those
systems and what they'd like to see with
them. Um Peter talked a little bit about
septic um and um I just want to kind of
reiterate that the the layout of these
lots is very deliberate mainly because
of the septic systems. We want to stay
under the 7,500 gallons per day that is
maximum allowed right now. It was just
updated um by the state for those
systems. Otherwise, you go into deep in
that permitting process for a large
centralized system in last years.
There's public hearings. Um the last
project I was on, um they it took so
long to get deep approval that they had
to go back to planning and zoning 11 and
get reapproved for the the project.
zone. We'd like to manage the septic um
individually on each lot. Um so all the
septic that's laid out is in
consideration with setbacks, separation
distances to well buildings to under
drains um that sort of a thing. Um and
they're all very conservative umly uh
laid out and shown. Um so those testing
is still needed. recommend at least a
couple test performance engineered
design. Um perhaps for the master plan
phase, we may do some soils testing to
confirm that what's out there can handle
um septic just so we're sure. Um we'd
also recommend doing at least one um uh
domestic well test so that we make sure
that the roofer can handle it
development.
Um and then finally the last thing is
electric telling data. It's always a
question from commissions. Um we'd pull
from Route 6 or 87 wherever it's
available and everything would be
underground. Um there'll be um each site
would have it own transformer pad close
to the building.
>> Question about that. Um any thoughts
about solar?
>> We haven't talked about that.
>> We've talked about it internally
and it's just the amount we would need
for this. we don't have the footprint to
do
>> and and the cost
cuz I have solar in my house and the
cost seems to be just way too much.
>> We we we don't we don't have the
footprint to be able to do. So we'd have
to we'd have to take a minimum of like
16 acres.
>> Oh. If you're going to put it on the
ground.
>> Yeah.
>> Yeah. Assuming the profiles the the roof
lines aren't going to be useful for
rooftop. Well, not on the designs that
we have on these buildings because they
have dormers on the top of each one of
them. We did look actually look into the
ones that sit there and pivot. They're
up on on stands, but now you're going to
have to line those up and and now you
got a bit of an eyesore
issues.
>> Snow load issues, too.
when you have things like that in the
roof.
>> If if there was another 16 acres of land
fairly close by, I mean, we get to a
solar development, it would help feed
this develop,
>> right?
As far as putting it on this current
property was just not would have to
start scattering all over the place. And
>> and on rooftops, when you think about
it, not every roof will work um because
of the tree stands and how they face.
And there a lot of they they they they
twist around a lot on the site. Uh so
some units could have solar and some not
and that could be problematic or how do
what do you do with the power and just
it's insufficient for the whole complex.
What do you do and ongoing maintenance
and the cost associated with it? They
pay for all that they're paying you and
all that stuff all the time and gets
very complicated. Unfortunately
might be a different story. They're all
going to be sold units and individual
owner say, "Hey, I want solar on my
roof." Um, then they pay for it as a
add-on. Um, but these are all rental
units and this means more people can get
into them. They don't have to have that
big down payment. Um, and more people
can afford these units because they're
right there. You just have to basically
pay. You don't require big huge deposit
or anything like pay advanced payment or
anything.
>> A couple years.
Okay. So, so you can so these would be
available to a lot of people who don't
have great wealth and don't have a lot
you know in savings um or high income.
Okay, which is the idea
and unless they have to put into some of
these other costs such as concrete
sidewalks off the side of the road, the
more they put into units and keep the
cost of the rental costs down and you
know with what's happening since CO
started. I mean the cost of building
these things is out of just out of
control.
>> Do we require sidewalks and
subdivisions? We haven't had a
subdivision in quite a while.
>> Yes. So there is I know you said nobody
uses them but are they included in here?
>> Um we didn't include them in here. We
included um block hole area and the 6T
path in within that pavement area in the
roadway.
>> So that's instead of the sidewalk that's
included in the 30 ft that you
>> Yeah. So it's 24 foot two two-way. We've
done a lot of that many developments and
then uh and then it continues to you
know just look this part of the pavement
be market to differentiate you probably
have some signage and and then that's
that's a multimodal path bicyclist
walkers
skateboarders I suppose
>> it's one of the things we discussed in
the April meeting
that more than obviously you guys didn't
give any answers something felt it was
more than acceptable to the sidewalk.
>> Okay. So that's kind of in L of
sidewalks.
>> Yes.
>> And then what
>> what would the pavement consist of?
>> It wouldn't be the vehicular traffic,
but for the people walking side
>> le the way I understand it essentially
it's a 30 foot wide road with a 6 foot
wide pedestrian bicycle lane
>> correct built into it.
>> Okay. All right. Thank you,
>> lady. 24 ft for vehicles.
>> Two-way traffic. Yeah. And that's that.
We do that all the time. Multi family
developments all over the place. 24 ft
>> as a concept.
>> Everything's a concept right now,
>> right?
>> Even the master plan will be an advanced
concept without the full engineer.
So going back to the question about
solar. So you you wouldn't at least
consider solar on the storage units and
the retail space.
>> Well, Japan will as far as far as the
retail space, we would be looking at
putting um AC units up there. It' be a
flat roof, AC units, heating units, and
stuff like that. Um there there may be
room for solar. We really didn't after
looking at
>> I'm just asking questions.
>> Well, I'm not ask if I can jump in here.
This is Leslie. And so we did. So just
if you look at um uh the the from a an
an energy or from a power uh
perspective, the the marginal cost to
set up the solar across not just the
housing units, but both the retail and
um uh uh the uh the self- storage units.
Um it it's it's really cost prohibitive
for what we're trying to do here. And so
it's just not feasible in any way for
this project based on just the initial
assessments that we've done um for the
the various intended use that we have we
have all around. And so I just you know
I don't I don't want to uh you know lead
the conversation down that path uh when
we've already been there and and we know
that it's it's cost prohibitive in this
specific uh case.
>> Thank you.
>> Any storage that's climate control? No.
>> And also the your regulations imply a
slope roof on everything. And the idea
as of right now, we're talking about the
main commercial building, the 15,000
foot building, and then the self storage
units, we're talking about a relatively
gently sloping, not a speaker roof or
anything like that
or a commercial building.
They don't necessarily put bright
orange.
We don't know that.
That's what they all were with storage
years ago. Bright orange or red
need sunglasses to look at something.
>> Any other questions?
like the uh so we had talked at one
point at least as a question about
designated affordable housing. They're
all they're all affordable units but
would uh your company be willing to go
through the administration required to
designate some affordable so that the
town would get credit for a couple of
those.
>> We're not doing very well right. We we
we talked about this in the April
meeting and and you guys were looking at
what how many units you guys were
thinking if and that was something you
guys were going to kind of come back
with and say, "Well, can you give us
eight? Can you give us 10?" So, it was
it was something you guys were going to
kind of discuss internally
and kind of throw back at us and say,
"This is what we're kind kind of like
what we talked about today on the on the
one. you guys are going to talk about
that kind of kind of throw that back at
us and say just what we're looking for.
>> So the state is hung up on 10% number,
>> right?
>> No, not necessarily.
>> Our housing affordable course drives the
gold. So
>> you have 3.85% right now.
>> Yeah. 51 units last I checked this
afternoon. and uh in a band it's gone
down
that year too.
>> Yeah, but if we were to get
you know 30 that
>> and I don't think you're going to agree
with the the cost that you're going to
ask is consistent with what it would be
to be designated affordable anyhow. It's
just there's more advent that goes on.
They'd be they'd be affordable for 40
years. Y
>> at 80% of the average median income. Y
>> which means they and it used to be not
that long ago and I've talked to the
most perhaps the number one affordable
housing attorney in the state of
Connecticut. He's very highly regarded,
great guy.
He told me years ago when I first talked
to him, he said 80%
uh average median income for the it's a
Hartford, West Hartford, East Hartford
market, rental market area.
It used to be you could break even on
those units, the developer. You just
here's your cost and it's a wash. Okay?
And then you want to make you make money
on the other units. Now
everybody loses a lot of money on 60% if
you go to HS30G
it's 15% at 60% average median income
you lose your shirt and then the the 80%
you also lose your shirt which is worse
with the 60%. So, if you don't get low
income tax credits and other special cut
rate financing, CHFA and that type stuff
and and all kinds of other gimmicks they
have, if you don't do that and these
guys are not used to that, you can't you
may not do a project.
>> Okay, it's that extent. So, it's tough.
Um, and you know, at 10%, you know,
we're talking about 110 units, so we're
talking about 11 units. That's they'd be
losing money on all 11 units of
substantial farms. So if we provide a
lot of units and they're not too big and
they're accessible to a lot more people,
they don't have it now. We're making a
lot of progress. If we if we go with
10%.
That's a lot of units and they're they'd
have to do a costbenefit analysis. See
if it makes any sense.
>> Yeah.
>> So can I jump in on that?
>> Yes, John, please.
>> So yeah. So, and again, I I would take I
would take our eye off the the 10% ball
a little bit um because that's it's it's
a little unrealistic and it's not truly
a target. That is really just a
threshold that that separates
communities that are subject to 830G and
communities that are not subject to
830G. We're we're about to go through an
exercise through the COG and through the
state in which each municipality will be
given a target number for new
developments uh new new housing
development. We don't know what the
number is yet. Um, obviously we know
that we need more than the, you know,
the number in Andover is going to be
more than 51 or whatever the current the
current restricted number is for a a
project like this unless you know the
state is going to drop a giant bag of
money onto the project to help subsidize
it.
You know, I just because these guys
aren't necessarily and I push back a
little bit on Peter, just because these
guys aren't aren't necessarily familiar
or used those tax credit programs in the
past, I wouldn't dismiss out of hand the
possibility
um of considering it. That said, um I
think,
you know, we would very very much
welcome and appreciate some set aside.
Um, and I think in the in the relatively
near term before you get too deep into
uh the engineering of this,
I I would appreciate sitting down with,
you know, even in a relatively informal
way to look through, you know, your
broad proformas and what you hope and
anticipate renting these units for
because if we're using if we're using
the lighter criteria, basically the
incentive housing criteria that Peter
described, which is an which is you know
somewhere 20% or less of the units at
80% of median. Um you know it could be
relatively close to the market rate
rents that you will be seeking. Um, and
you know, just as an example, and again,
you know, new construction is a little
bit different, but the the the woman,
and I I forget her her name, um, that
owns the owns the um uh existing
apartments
um in the in the uh western part of
town. Um,
her her rents that she's charging right
now, something like 1,600 bucks a month
to 1,800 bucks a month, actually
probably are would be affordable to the
80% median. So her her market rents are
technically affordable except that
they're not restricted that way. So I
would just be curious and well more than
curious. Um very interested to to get a
sense of and you don't have to answer
this now and I'm sure you you know this
is going to take us number crunching
what the anticipated market anticipated
market rents are and where we are
relative to our 80% median. Um because I
think it you know the the the only real
heavy lift there might be that they will
be restricted going forward. But again
if if your if your target rents are
basically affordable
um you know as the state might define it
then then the lift is just will we you
know take on doing the the necessary
paperwork. Um, so I I would encourage
you I you know I'm not necessar and
because you know these things are
extraordinarily expensive and you know
if a town gets too heavy-handed with its
affordable requirement it can very very
easily kill a project. Um but so I would
just encourage everyone involved and
particularly developers to keep an open
mind about what their
you know their proforma looks like and
and leave open the possibility that that
some of these units could be pretty
close um to affordable and then and then
maybe it's you know you you increase
your market rents 50 bucks a month and
and your affordable you drop them 50
bucks a month and and you're all set.
Um, so I would encourage sharpening of
the pencils a little bit just for the
the sake of understanding if this could
work before we before the town sort of
drops the hammer and says, "No, you got
to do it."
>> I I like that idea, John. Just I looked
up I' I've looked at them before, you
know, the average median income uh for
the area and then they have it by how
many uh bedrooms there are in it. And
they also say that you have to deduct
for utilities,
>> right? So,
>> it's an all-in, right? It's an all-in
number.
>> Yeah. Yeah. Yeah. So, you have utilities
and I I couldn't understand whether or
not you have to deduct for the heat
heating system for the unit. I didn't
they weren't they were unclear what I
was looking at today, but you so you
take the market rate and you may have to
deduct for utilities and for some other
factors such as heat. I'm not sure about
that. Um, so it can bring it right down
where they're taking a loss on everyone.
Uh, and it could be substantial. I just
don't know that. And you also have to
pay uh you know attorney and other
people to come up with a commitment for
40 years uh and the regulations and all
that stuff and who's going to be
monitoring it and all that stuff you
have to get for somebody for that. So
there are other factors, but I like your
idea, John. I think we it's worth
looking at. Um they don't know what the
rent might be because right now we are
we're a ways off from construction,
>> right?
>> So we don't know what the cost of a 2x4
is. Uh and let alone uh fuel cost,
diesel or whatever for the equipment um
you know the cost of the road. We don't
we don't know that stuff right now
because it's far off to know where the
rents would be and what's the
marketplace at that point. So, it's
really early to to forecast that. Um, so
there are a lot of factors here, but
it's worth taking a look at. You're
right. But you must have some kind of
you must have some kind of math in your
head to be able to move forward with the
project, right?
>> It's almost math in my head.
>> So, so far they're still going forward.
Um, they've se they've seen a lot of
costs. are starting to get those costs
in, but they don't have all of them yet.
So, they're still going forward, but um
you know, it could be a point where hey,
it's not profitable.
>> Um all the all the the units have
electric heat electric
>> many
typical mit
uh or there other brands. There's just
ton of them.
>> It's because I know there
volume.
>> So there'll be'll
be'll be green.
>> It'll be considered and that's be
outside and and the plan will be to put
the condenser right up behind it the
apartment itself.
>> And that's considered green. It's not
oil furnace.
>> It wouldn't sit on the ground. It would
be mounted right onto the house and
brackets.
>> Sure. And they they're used all the time
now. on there. They tend to be very very
efficient. Now you can even have the
cold cold weather they still operate.
Whereas they used to not
went below freezing was a real problem.
>> And then you heat your AC off more.
>> Yep.
>> So installation costs aren't bad.
>> So you end up with a better unit at a
lower cost.
that it
>> questions what I mean my what do you
what do you guys think this something
that we we can make these changes where
you know John and Wayne and this is
something we all can get behind I mean I
I know you guys can't give approval
right now just
inform.
>> I mean, because because if if this is
something you guys can get behind, then
we can really start spending some money
on the engineering and and and all the
things that need to get done during
these three months, four months. I don't
know why Peter's got 26 years going on
this project.
But, you know, we're really just trying
to get a good feel for for what you guys
think, what you guys
are going to allow, you know, and if
this is something that you think you
guys can all get kind of with the text
amendments and stuff. Um, I would like
to start pushing forward.
Well, if if I could say something like
um this is this is a big project for
this little town.
>> It's a huge project. It's something that
I don't believe any any of us have
>> right tackled
and there are some things from the
commissioner's perspective from the
town's perspective. This is going to
need to to go go by our uh the
commission's uh attorney. It's going to
need to go by the town engineer.
It's going to need to go by DPW.
Uh
that isn't to say that that should be
impeded. That should just be the normal
process that that it has to be looked at
by by people with uh more expertise than
than any of us have
and frankly that's going to be an
additional expense.
But
I I know you're you're
you want to get moving. I get it. I get
it. Money time time is money.
>> Mhm.
>> And u you know, as far as getting behind
it is concerned.
My job is to do what the commission
tells me to do. So
I can kind of say it's up to these guys.
you with saying that. I mean, like the
town engineer and the town lawyer,
they're not going to be somebody who
would be able to say no. They're just
going to say, "Well,
>> well, if you guys
point, they'll adise the commission. I
mean, at some point, you're going to
have a cross-section of what the road's
going to look like or you're going to
need an engineer to look at that and
say, "Yeah, that that'll work." And all
right, and all that good stuff. Our
engineering because this this is a big
project. This isn't a driveway.
the green.
>> Yeah. I mean, you fully expect a third
party review,
>> right,
>> done on a detailed site plan,
>> but that that's going to come later.
>> Yeah.
>> When you do your master plan and then
ultimately the application for
either the site plan or special permit
um and you have the actual engineering
to look at you, we're not anywhere close
to that yet.
>> We are the town engineers for towns. We
do that type of thing.
I get it. We have our own
>> Oh, no. I know. We're not saying
>> we wear who is your
>> We use We use Barton and Legudas
primarily, I believe.
>> Excuse me.
>> I don't we use Barton and Legudas for
review.
>> Well,
>> currently it's Brober is doing the
bridge on Lake Road. So I'm assuming he
for the town, right?
>> Probably start.
>> Yeah.
>> Well,
>> whoever it is, I'll figure it out.
>> Yeah. Yeah. We we'll deal with whoever
you guys select. Yeah.
>> I haven't had to consult an engineer
yet. This will be the first time.
So, uh, I'm just going to throw it out
there because we're a small town and
this is like everybody's already agreed
this is like the biggest
development we've ever seen. And so
furthermore, we still have the small
town uh mindset on like, okay, well, I I
get that
we you would like to have the town plow
the roads, but I'm kind of seeing this
more like like a condo association where
they take care of their own road for
plowing and maintenance and uh as maybe
maybe there's some legal requirements
for the storm water management, ponds,
maintenance. I'm not sure if we're
capable of that. See where I'm going
with that? So I know we there's a little
bit of back and forth hashing that has
to get done there. Um besides the zone
zone change and tax amendments and the
change of the master floating plan. Uh
but I think that you know we are in line
with our plan of conservation
development. If you would agree uh do
you agree with that statement John?
>> Uh yeah I think absolutely.
So personally I I mean I personally
would like to see this go forward and
if we can just work out all these
details and uh you know then we are
going to have to have some public
hearings and then I don't like you were
stating about we might need three as of
right now absolutely three unless we
combine them and that's a greater risk
for our client
by doing three we have time frame but if
we do the
>> zoning text amendment maybe not the zone
change to be. Um and we do it concurrent
with the uh master plan
um and the zone change application which
if we if we agree if you you agree with
John and Wayne and us about reducing the
requirements for the zone change and
master plan the master plan elements
they require all kinds of sophisticated
reports and every one of the pages of
those reports that recorded in the town
cler's office they make $60 a page
during FY11 something like that you if
we can cut in some of those requirements
for that stage and leave it to this
engineered cycling stage. Um, we can
maybe do that. Um, and and and and
exposure with Sean and his partners is a
lot less and timeless money for them.
More applications we have, the more
timeless involved consultants and more
expensive it is.
>> I gotcha. And and just, you know, full
disclosure, you know, all the commission
members are elected. We don't get paid
for this. So all the burden of these uh
text amendment changes are going to be
on John Kiscowski and then we're going
to vote on them. So
>> just keep that in mind. I mean we're
what do you you think you're going to be
able to handle the workload, John? Would
you and your
>> Well, I you know I I it depends on what
we're talking about. I mean you know the
answer is yes. Of course. Um I wouldn't
I wouldn't suggest that I would be
writing the revised language. I would
not be preparing the application for a
text amendment. This would come out of
conversations with the applicants and
Wayne and I will, you know, look at what
they want to do
>> and and advise them advise them of the
areas that would need change um in order
to enable this. That's that's our role
here is to review their proposals
relative to current regulations or their
reg their proposed regulations relative
to what the town is envisioning you know
per the master plan and and per what
they want to do. So yeah of course we'll
we're you know as far as I'm concerned
and and hopefully as far as Wayne is
concerned we are happy to engage with
these guys but we're not you know we're
not preparing their application for
them. We'll write them and we'll present
them to John and Wayne and then we'll
discuss it with them. See if they are
comfortable with it or if they suggest
any further changes and we'll rewrite
them working with other clients.
>> We do that all the time.
>> So c can you just quick go over what you
were talking about as far as combining
things.
>> So in so
>> I think I missed it.
>> Okay. So
you're not allowed to apply for things
unless you're conforming to zoning. So,
but it because before it's an engineered
site plan, you probably can apply for
the master plan if it's predicated on a
zoning text amendment first. So, if we
apply for that, maybe it maybe it's
currently maybe two separate
applications. Maybe they're handled
backtoback hearings. So, you have the
first hearing. I'm thinking John out
loud here. Um, you have the first
hearing. You have for the zoning text
amendments. We don't need the zone
change for the B zone. Then we do the
zoning text amendments. We have that. We
have the hearing on that. Uh and then
you have the hearing on the other uh
which is the uh master plan and the um
uh master plan and the zone change
itself to the overlay zone. Okay. The
floating zone. Uh but before you act on
the zone change and the master plan, you
have to first act it on the text
amendments. That's for attorney. Mark
Prince is your attorney. You said so
then he'd have to come and say yeah he's
comfortable with that. If he isn't then
we have to go back to three steps
>> okay
>> with the plane zone and we also have to
be comfortable with not going to the
wetlands commission at each step that we
actually wait till we have an engineered
site plan which would be the third step
or maybe the second step if everything
is combined.
>> So sounds like what you're really
talking about is having the public
hearing for the text amendment and the
public hearing for the master plan on
the same at the same meeting. That's the
only way I can see to cut it back cost
for these guys and
>> but not necessarily combining any you're
not skipping any step.
>> No.
>> Right. Yeah.
>> All right.
>> But attorney Branch has become I'm sure
he'll say, "Hey, you can do it that way.
We apply under that regulation, but
you've adopted the regulation before you
act on it." And he may say, "Oh, the
appeal period has go by before you can
act on the second one." I don't know. At
least
>> let us know. the presentations can be
done in one night.
>> Yep.
>> And having the consultants there where
they have an architect there, um a
traffic engineer, all stuff, if it can
be done in one night, you know, they can
buy an hourly basis for that type of
work and it saves Sean and his part as
well.
>> I I get it.
>> And it saves a lot of time. Time is
going
>> Yep.
>> One more question. I think these are
just month-to-month rentals. Is there
like a lease agreement? We would be
looking for 12-month leases and then
obviously once the 12 months I would
like another 12 months but you know we
can't force everybody to sign another
lease
>> right so it's your problem
>> sounds good 10 year leases
>> occasionally have a tendency
bills or nuisance to neighbors whenever
came around there
>> and this is going to remain under
your control.
>> Yeah, we have no we we have no plan on
selling
>> because I know there's there's a few
LLC's involved, but so it may be
transferred between LLC's that you and
your partners are.
>> We we have not created the LLC for this
yet. So, we are under our different one
of our different LLC's right now.
>> So, you
>> we're going to create a whole new LLC
just for this typical.
>> Okay. All gotcha. Okay.
All right.
>> Well, this has been very helpful. Thank
you so and uh for coming and thank you
John and Wayne for your been great.
>> Thank you.
>> Yes. Thank you very much guys.
>> Can I make a comment then?
>> Oh yes. Go ahead.
>> Marcy from economic value.
>> Oh hi.
>> Um personally I see this as very
positive. Uh there's been a lot of
people that have been trying to
encourage businesses in town and uh
obviously like you said being dos there.
Um the one thing that I actually got a
text from a whole bunch of people when
they first heard about this just
yesterday and they were all freaking out
because they're worried about more kids
in the school. So, I think that, you
know, to encourage you to to lean more
towards more efficiency apartments, more
um studios in one bedrooms. I know it's
a popular thing. I think the Whisy
Hills, they have garden apartments and
they're looking to add because they fill
them up. They never have any sites. I
mean, we can definitely take a look at
that and do the market study, but um
what we've been finding a lot of is
people are sharing apartments. You know,
friends will get two bed brothers or
sisters will get two bedrooms together
so they can split all the cost of
everything just because the cost of
everything is so high in countries.
>> Yeah. On people that live like
there are going to be inexpensive
requirements. So if we look I look I
looked at the plan conservation
development it was just it's not very
old 2024 right and they did a survey of
the town and public hearings and the
commission elected commission adopted it
and they said that the problem is we're
losing kids in the schools elementary
and in RAM and middle school and the
high school we need children coming in
we want to be a place for families
population is aging we want to be
welcoming to families and for people who
grow up in town, be able to stay in
town. That was important. So, so there's
an element in town
>> you're listening to.
>> Yeah.
>> Okay. Everyone's got their own business.
There's there's that element in every
town.
>> Right. Right.
>> Yeah.
>> They think more kids going to make their
taxes go higher no matter what. So, but
>> yeah, I I I get some towns where I just
every time we get hammered about
anything to do with children. Um, you
know, most communities supposed to be,
you know, for families and stuff, but
you know, we get I I tell you, I need a
flat jacket.
>> And she's
put my
>> I put my kids through the schools and
they're done well. They run off to
college and stuff like that, but and I'm
still it's been over 20 years I've been
paying for other kids, people's kids.
That's the way it works.
>> I have noticed you guys talked about was
roundabouts. we have room for
roundabouts about doing those instead of
stop signs. We didn't think about that.
Um, personally, I like avoiding them
because they take up so much space. If
you get a home,
>> like if you like
>> the smallest you can possibly go is the
disaster that's in Glastonbury. I'm sure
everyone heard about it. The trailer
>> and those are about 75 right. get a
tractor trailer through a roundabout
like not that there would be tractor
trailer but it would be a 200 foot wide
radius
>> um for and then for fire you would need
a minimum of 100 ft to maneuver that.
So, um, we can look at it. Um,
I it's just something that we just
didn't think out there.
>> They're done at They're done typically
when there's a high volume and you have
like three, four, five intersection
coming in. They got great Ellington five
corners, for example, is a great
example. I love what they did there. I
used to go through it there all the
time. You live in Vernon, right? I used
to go there all the time. and and by
putting in that that roundabout
fantastic traffic flows through fewer
accidents everything goes less energy
use for everybody and it's a great idea
but in the middle of a a relatively this
is relatively small develop for Andovers
it's huge but it's a relatively small
development the traffic volumes are
going to be very small I
I don't see the need for that in this
development going to slow the traffic
down if people push speed through some
of these straight lines some bumps.
>> Yeah. And when we first Lawrence design
and we're working with the grates too,
it worked out very well. You're not
going straight through here. There's no
strip here. And also by taking the 30
foot wide street and narrowing down with
markings and other things, signage and
stuff, you you you slow the traffic down
the speeds. And there are many ways of
doing that. You ever been to Evergreen
Walk? You see at the intersections, you
know, they run a stop sign. People go
across stuff, but they they narrow it
down. They bring things into it.
Landscaping, sidewalk, stuff like, and
people go slower through there. You only
see going 60 through the middle of
Evergreen. They do a nice job on
Evergreen Walk. I think the other thing
too is you get all the best beans are
off the street crossing, too.
>> So, they're all
>> they should be.
>> They should be.
>> They shouldn't be off the street,
>> but they're out there on their phone in
the middle of the street. That's
natural.
But uh you know I I think the the trick
is making sure that that the traffic is
moving a safe space. So people are on
the road even if it's on a designated
shoulder that they're going to be all
right.
>> One thing just one thing about people
opposed because they're concerned about
kids and it costs money to educate them.
the population has gone down overall
although it's a little bit uptick I
think in in they go down so the number
of kids in each classroom goes down and
so you have fewer kids in elementary
school the cost to operate that school
still the principal still the heating
unit teachers just smaller classes
you may find out the cost per goes up a
lot when you the population is
here right now
>> same
That's what she told
their first everyone's texting me saying
this is you know so another thing I
wanted to mention what I like about this
>> is that they
it's not going to be our case and a lot
of people are concerned about our coins
now and so like you know I think that
you know if you accentuate that that you
know the view you're going to see from
the road is that be just a sore
which was the exact intention. We want
the store front and center so there can
be customers coming off the roadways.
Even the storage units be pulled back
off the road. It was a little bit better
for the design. Um and there'll be a
sign on the fix they know to get up in
there. But the goal is to really hide
those storage units because the rest of
the living arena neither. So we'll come
up with the design and kind of tuck them
away, have the units tucked away. So
like you said, like if you drive, right,
you drive right by and you don't even
know there's
access to want to do that. We just have
interior.
>> Yeah. Yep.
>> People know they're
not a lot of that.
>> Yeah. Thank you.
>> Thank you guys. All right. Thank you
guys very much. Thank you. We do a lot
more technology and thank you. No, I
think we learned a lot.
Thank you.
>> It passed. It did pass.
>> Oh, good.
>> It ran past AR now. We don't know about
others.
>> Thank you. Okay.
>> Thank you. AES
>> AES.
>> Thank you.
>> You're welcome.
>> But yeah, I got a whole bunch of
messages yesterday.
>> I just got Roy C.
>> Oh, really? Oh, yeah. Oh, no.
>> Not too many.
>> This would be a huge deal. But I think
it would be great. I think it would be
one in our meeting. Anyway,
>> yeah. Thanks for the information.
>> Thanks, Mar.
No, no, we got we got four of you here.
>> Is there anything on the agenda you all
want to skip?
Um
like go to uniform.
Well, how about this? Can you uh brief?
I mean, I I looked at it briefly. The
the the tour reform and I guess we could
push that to the next meeting if
wants to review.
>> Okay.
>> Sure.
>> Curious. We've got a form.
>> Yeah.
>> I think that's predicated on a special
permit application. Is it not? Well, it
could be for both. I I I have the form
for for either
either
either a um
a farm related event
>> or a non-farm related event which
requires a special permit. Yeah.
>> Right. Okay.
So,
you know, the concern I have is be is I
look on Facebook and I see a string of
concerts going on over Farm this summer.
>> Yeah.
>> And I see no special permit application
come in.
>> You haven't? Have you
>> and I'd like to head off that being an
issue?
>> There's something later coming to that
effect.
>> Okay. um not specifically to that but
but that is related to that property.
>> So we would be skipping that.
>> It's going to come upon a report.
>> Yes.
>> Okay.
Skip that.
>> Hearing no objections. Moving on to new
business B where you received a special
permit. Go ahead, Wayne.
>> Um yeah, 12 Center Street. Uh originally
uh
Nahan Orto had uh in 2024 had originally
applied for or his original application
in 2024 included a uh an accessory
apartment. Um, it's my understanding
that Jim
talked him out of that or for some
reason he removed that special
apartment, that accessory apartment and
um
the uh single family dwelling was
approved by uh
in and as of right approval. Um
he uh
wants to go ahead and put the accessory
apartment in. Uh he's not changing the
footprint of the building. Footprint of
the building is going to stay the same
exactly the same. And the area above the
garage is going to be dedicated to the
accessory apartment. I I have the the uh
site plan. I have the elevations and the
floor plan. Everything is checking out
so far. I did ask his his engineer to go
to Eastern Highland Health District to
make sure that nothing nothing would
change with that because the number of
bedrooms is going to remain the same.
with it's it's going to be uh yeah, the
number of bedrooms is going to remain
the same, but I just want to make sure
that um Eastern Highlands is okay with
it. Uh and I have no reason to think
they wouldn't be.
So, right now, we're just looking at um
accepting an application and set public
hearing date.
Sounds good.
>> And I've had some conversations with the
engineer that's involved with this and
hopefully
this project is going to move ahead. He
did grade around the lot. He got that
bulldozer going and did some did some
grading, cleaned the lot up. Looks much
more presentable now than it did a
couple weeks ago. Uh at least from that
perspective.
But it's still just a shell.
It's been a while.
It's been a
almost two years
in various stages of construction
and it's right now it's still just a
shell.
So
we put in the application and we need a
special hearing because he wants to do
this as a market rate accessory
apartment.
And the fellow who is the applicant is
planning on living in the house.
Oh. Uh, yes. His daughter.
His daughter.
>> I think our regulation requires that the
property owners live in the house.
>> It does.
It does.
>> I can't answer that question.
>> Yeah. Okay.
>> That question can be answered
public hearing.
>> Yep.
at the public hearing or before the
public hearing and that question can be
answered and that will will inform
whether there actually will be a public
hearing. Let's put it that way.
Because if the answer is no, then Bob's
going to say,
there's no point in having a public
hearing now, is there?
You want to tenatively put it on the
schedule for July?
>> I'll make a motion that we put public
hearing from the department on the
schedule for July 8 second.
>> Yeah, the application is withdrawn. It's
withdrawn, right?
>> All in favor?
Henry
>> I
motion passes 500.
>> All right. Correspondence. Very long. Um
but maybe this is the time I can
correspondence.
Let's see.
school.
>> I might have left that.
>> Well, actually is running.
>> Yeah. Why don't we Why don't we table
that for
for my
uh
zoning agent report. Can we do that?
That has the correspondence that's
included in some nasty I recently sent
out.
So, you want to do you want to skip one
and include one and the other?
>> Yeah. The correspondence really is about
um some letters I I sent out uh
concerned violations.
>> Okay.
>> And you knew or don't talk about that
now?
>> Yeah.
>> Well, we can talk about it now or talk
about it when I do my zoning agent
report.
>> Okay. That was my question. Okay. So,
we're tableabling the rest of
correspondence.
>> Yeah. There is well there there is no no
correspondence. I'll say
>> can I can I'm sorry. Can I can I jump in
real quick?
>> Yeah.
>> And Wayne, could I ask you to stop the
share? I I think you don't need the
special permit up there right now.
>> All right.
>> Um so just technically speaking, um the
referral that we got uh you're closing
the window, not stopping the share.
What am I doing? Did this a wrong
>> red box at the top?
>> Oh,
>> thank you.
>> Um the the you know, technically
speaking, um the referral that we got
from uh Bolton about their proposed
middle housing regulation would probably
fall under correspondence. It's it's not
technically a mandatory referral. A lot
of towns keep sending those things out.
They don't have to, but I would just
note it that it was and I believe Wayne
distributed it. Um, so that's that's an
item of correspondence of note.
>> Thank you, John.
Go ahead.
>> Yep. The town of Halton has done some
regulations. They made a referral to
listing.
>> Yeah.
>> All right. Uh, I guess we'll go on to
commission discussion. So,
>> okay. I I had sent the commission
members
a draft of
or
really it was my thoughts when I when I
look at the regulations and the ability
to recover costs legal of the uh for for
reviews um by professionals.
I didn't find anything in our
regulations except when it came to storm
water management that specifically said
the commission going to recover cost for
engineering or or legal review. Uh, I I
approached attorney Brandt about that
and he
um confirmed
my
research in that the town actually has
to have an ordinance
in place to recover those costs. The
current ordinance that
talks about fees as far as zoning is
concerned only empower only sets fees
for proc receiving and processing
uh permits. It doesn't specifically say
anything about recovering legal costs
for engineering costs. So to that end, I
drafted a
um a proposed ordinance really not a
zoning regulation, a proposed ordinance
that I'm looking for input from from the
commission
and u ultimately
u
approval by the commission to to send it
to the board the selectment for
that process could turn it into an
ordinance.
Um,
as we learned as we had today with this
project here,
I believe the town's going to reverse
some significant costs involved with
engineering review and legal review.
And I and
I believe that the commission should
shouldn't want those kinds of reviews
for a project like this.
So I did not print it out for you guys.
I have it here.
>> You did email it to us. So
>> I did email it to everybody.
>> And I don't know if anybody's looked at
it. You guys want to if I'm going down
the right I'm going down the right path.
>> If Brg agrees with it, then we go. Yeah,
I'm I'm right there with you.
>> Well, attorney Branch has not reviewed
these exact words.
>> I got to
>> he said a few words which were several
pages more than I got here.
>> Okay.
So
>> do you mind if I get back?
>> It's just this draft is just kicking
tires.
>> Yeah. Um
>> basically I want the once uh if the
commission is okay, I'll I'll send that
off to attorney Brand. He's probably
going to want to add a lot to it.
Um,
look at the John, have you looked at it?
>> Um, I only looked at it briefly. I I I
didn't I didn't spend much time with it.
>> Yeah,
I I
borrowed a lot of those words from
towns around us.
No sense reinvent the wheel.
Was there something about a certain
dollar amount for subdivisions and then
a certain dollar amount for the first
three lots on a subdivision?
>> Yeah, that's that's the current the
current fee structure in um
actually our fee structure
is an entire we're charging fees that
aren't in the ordinance.
I I thought it said you're what you're
charging now is like $10 higher than
what's in the ordinance.
>> Yeah,
>> we're charging like $150 for something.
>> The ordinance says
>> 140.
>> I don't know how we can do that, but
we're doing that.
>> RP
ridiculously low compared to other
towns.
I have
>> I know you sent out a bunch of uh
examples from your town, right? It would
be nice spreadsheet that says I tried to
do that. You know,
>> they do things a little different. It's
hard to hard to compare
>> big round. And it's hard to compare, you
know, specific
um
>> well
like we'll we'll take we'll take this
planning uh proposal for an example. the
um the tax money coming in after they
get something built should in theory
cover
any of our engineering double-checking
fees and attorneys fees.
>> That's most town. No, no, I I did
research ordinances and I got
>> and every town I checked town that
borders this town.
>> Yep.
>> Has an ordinance.
>> Yeah. that that that authorizes the
recovery of legal fees.
>> We don't have that.
>> And Jay brought up a good point. If that
the development doesn't happen and we
spend all that time and money, then it's
gone. I get it.
So,
>> do we vote on some of this to the board?
I
>> I don't think you need to vote on it.
What I'm not what I want is
>> is does the commission support what I'm
doing?
>> I do.
>> And I will forward this on to attorney
Grants for to get his eyes.
>> Okay, sounds good.
>> And then bring it back to you uh next
meeting as a more formal proposal.
>> Thanks, Wayne.
>> Thank you. I've seen some things in the
past, but it wasn't to do with what
we're talking about now, but and I don't
remember what they were, so I can't
really say anything, but sometimes I
think things can be a little too high,
but I can't remember what I was looking
at in the past.
>> Zoning fees aren't the zoning fees
aren't so high. Building permit fees are
a lot.
>> Yeah,
>> maybe that's
>> so people out there, they're pretty
significant. So, isn't that what's
theoretically supposed to cover the
engineering costs, the the building
permit fees?
>> Well, we're paying I don't know where
that
>> No, the the zoning zoning fees and
building permit fees could should be
kept separately.
>> Okay.
>> Um and and I just I just weigh in.
I I think um it's important to have an
ordinance like this to cover the town,
but I do think it should be relatively
narrow and we can we can talk to
attorney Brandt about this and and only
triggered by
um a basically a vote of the commission
that this is necessary. Like if it's a
complicated enough project that we need
a third party attorney, third party
engineer, third party, you know,
environmental scientist, whatever. Um,
it should be basically decided at the
time of application receipt when we know
that this is a complicated thing. Um,
and and you know, it should not be
open-ended so the developer is not just
on the hook for you know, tens or even
hundreds of thousands of dollars of
environmental review. should be a a
one-time, you know, uh fee in escrow
that would cover technical review. There
are there are good examples, and I think
Wayne's probably gathered some of them,
but um with complicated projects in a
relatively small town, you know, with
with, you know, we don't have in-house
engineering, you know, we don't have
in-house attorneys. It it is important
for the town not to go too far out of
pocket on this stuff. So, I I think it's
a valuable exercise.
Thank you, John.
>> That's all I got. I believe John's up
there next.
Go
>> ahead, John.
>> So, uh, yeah, and and this may this may
be a longer discussion than you guys
really really want to start at 9:20. Um,
but I will just note that I so I
forwarded around yesterday
um a a a
draft markup of the zoning regulations.
So because of uh public act 251 that
passed last November, um municipalities
have to make a couple of changes to
their zoning regulations in the
relatively short term um to accommodate
uh modifications to parking and
modifications to what's called middle
housing uh which is two through nine
units in um
in commercial districts. Um, so
what I have provided to you, and this is
maybe something that you guys want to
put off until next month to do sort of a
full walkth through, but what I prepared
in markup style um with your with your
zoning regulations, basically any new
language I've proposed in red here, um,
that is basically the minimum
reasonable in my mind, the the minimum
reasonable number of amendments that you
would have make to your zoning
regulations to get you compliant with
those provisions of public act 251.
Um and and they you know the the major
thing is well there's two sort of major
things is one you need to allow middle
housing in the business district um by
by a site plan. Um so I have proposed in
section 4 I a new section 4.23 23
um
here and I can make it a little bit
bigger if you want and and again I don't
want to go through this whole thing
because it's it's already late um uh
section 4.23 how we define what middle
housing should be broadly speaking
including um some considerations of
impervious coverage landscaping and
architectural design elements. I'm I'm
drawing from our existing regulations on
uh architectural design in the business
district which is section 83. Um
and then and then basically enabling
that in the business zone which is the
only zone you are required to allow
this. You don't have to put it in
residential zones. You don't have to put
it in industrial zones. Um it's business
and mixed use. And the only landed, you
know, obviously we have a mixeduse
overlay that's not landed. the business
zone is the only landed zone that this
change needs to apply to. Um so and
again, you know, the the the referral
that we got from Bolton um is really
elaborate. That's sort of, you know,
buying a buying a you know, a Range
Rover when the state is really only
asking for um a small Toyota. Um it's
it's a it's a a complicated set of regs.
I'm I tried to keep this as simple as
possible. Um but uh this is something
that we have to address and adopt sooner
than later. Um so I'm I'd really take
your guidance on how you'd like to
proceed and it maybe if you know right
now the only thing that we've got on the
agenda next month is that the you know
the public hearing for the accessory
department. It might be worth uh setting
aside time to walk through these next
month.
But I would ask I would ask I would ask
you all to look at the the markup that I
distributed to you all yesterday.
>> Yeah. And I've gone through but I think
that everybody should take the the next
month to really go through and figure
out if they want to add to it or
subtract it. And
I Sounds good.
>> Sounds good. All right. Thank you, John.
>> Yeah.
>> Keep that. put that on the agenda for
next month.
>> Okay.
>> And um we're on to administrative
reports. All right.
got there is I only have one
um
the one on the top is the most
interesting one
What's that?
>> No,
>> I'll just tell you. I'll just tell you
what this corresponding to was it was
not um looking for payment of this bill
of Holler and S's bill.
That was the Yep. Okay. um
>> an unpaid bill from
>> I thought we cleared that up last month
and that the new town treasurer took
care of that.
>> Uh apparently only one of the bills was
taken care of.
>> Okay. I I do understand that they're
still playing catchup.
>> Okay.
>> But we're going to need that.
>> I saw Brand said we're back in his good
graces. That's what I remember from last
month.
>> He did. He did.
We were okay.
Now we're not okay. We're back out of
the good graces.
So
that I mean I wanted I wanted attorney
Branch here today to listen to this.
>> But he didn't get paid.
>> But I'm not going to
>> Oh, right. We don't want to add to the
bill if we're not ready.
Right.
So on the Bunker Hill property, um
that's that
I have sent a note um
indicating that the car storage was
violated zoning regulations and inviting
the uh owner of the property
to apply for a special permit
which
he believes he doesn't need to apply for
um
>> is it installs
>> among other things that go on on the
property.
So I guess we have to start up we have
to start uh for lack of a better word
progressive discipline.
Um
issue issue formal notices of violation
and start down that road.
>> Wait, what's the address you talking
about?
>> Excuse me.
>> What was the address you're talking
about?
>> Um it's a fun road.
a uh
the site where the
um
pitch family farms Yeah.
As you can see, I
made it to Facebook
for that letter.
So, this issue you're talking about
isn't about the the the bands or the
music.
>> Well, that's that's another thing. this
right.
>> This is about um using a portion of the
property to store
cars that are um presumably moved um
looks like they're being moved from
auction to here and then being moved to
car lots wherever.
>> Yeah.
>> About
between Oh, I don't know.
10 and 15 maybe even 20 cars
at any one time may be parked there.
So
>> viewable from the road
>> and the zoning the zoning regulations
clearly state uh clearly say that um car
storage requires a special permit
and property zone industrial and
specifically says in the industrial zone
we have to have a special permit to do
that activity and the business and the
business alone says the same
that previous letter had going out
regarding
event an event the uh
funky monkey
that occurred on that property. again
inviting them to apply for a special
permit to hold that event.
>> Yeah, I thought his his
position was that that was not his
event. That was the over and over event.
>> The letter to both of them. Okay.
I didn't care who
did somebody.
>> Are they related?
Did those two properties related? Hand
over and over in the farm.
>> No, they're not related. The the the
funky monkey event happens on both
properties.
>> Just spills over.
>> Yeah. They've kind of been advertising
each other's activities.
Like if there's an event at one I mean
I'm not saying in every instance but
there have been times when there's an
event at one and then the other one
would hold an event and they kind of
cross advertise for each other.
>> I was unaware of the till Jed brought it
up the Facebook about the concerts. I I
don't I personally don't do Facebook
that Facebook posting is something my
wife found.
>> You're better off.
You're saying you're better off
>> better off without Facebook.
>> Facebook.
>> Um,
so and you requested that they you sent
a letter to both of them saying you need
a permit to do this. You haven't heard
back from either party.
>> Oh, I heard back from Mr. Fitch.
>> Fitch and then and you posted Facebook,
but you haven't heard from Andover.
So did
maybe between your two you can refresh
my memory was it position
applying for two different things and
didn't he kind of drop one of them?
>> Well yes he he started out applying for
the agro tourism regulation.
>> Okay.
>> And then
he withdrew it. We approve it.
>> That's the language. Okay. and but we
thought we needed a regulation anyhow.
So we just continued on down that path
and uh
read the regulation.
>> Okay. And is that what this form has to
do with that we switch to?
>> Yes.
>> Okay. The form. Okay. And then also
I don't remember if it was under that
umbrella or not. We had a discussion
about like if Ryan did get permission to
do certain things, would he need a
a permit for every single event or would
be left that permit or something. Yeah,
>> that's that's what you're talking about.
>> Okay. So, that's still up in the air.
>> Well, I think you can do a special
permit for a series of events.
>> Why not?
>> I think that's some of the discussion we
had. Were you here?
>> Yes. If you if you know what date, if
you know when the events are going to
occur, I don't see why you can't have
them all in one application.
>> And again, that's what's still in the
name.
>> What's up in the air
>> about
whether
you need to do that?
>> Well, he has he has to put in a special
permit application. That's what I'm
getting at. Yeah.
>> So, that's what we're we're talking
about. So, that has nothing to do with
the car storage. Well, that's a
different that's an unrelated issue on
the same on the same.
>> Okay. So, we're talking about both
whether or not we finish talking about
it tonight or not. But
>> when I move it when I when I go ahead,
I'm going to put them they're both going
to be on the same.
>> Okay.
>> I'll address them both with the same
notice.
So, do you want to wait and discuss that
when we discuss this agurism form
or is that what we're still deciding?
>> The the applying for the permit I I
don't think is dependent upon the form.
You can still apply for the special
permit.
>> You should I think that's a prerequisite
to using the form. He applies for a
special permit to do X, Y, and Z. And
Paul said he wants to do W. He puts in
the form. He's already got special
permit approved, new events, maybe that
covers it.
And as far as the
additional vehicles and the parking
where they're not supposed to be
parking, is that that's going to be
handled separately? Correct. like
because it is a business own. He is
allowed to have vehicles, but now it's
an automotive transfer station like you
were describing. That's a different
story, right? So, there's a couple
vehicles related to the business and a
truck coming in once in a while, but
it's not what we're talking about,
right? We're talking about a bunch of
cars parked in a carrier parked there
and
>> that out to a sub like a sublet
>> or
then
>> he needs to get a special permit for
that then, right?
>> Okay.
And that's just as simple as getting a
special permit and bringing
virtually.
>> It's as simple as applying for a special
permit and then the commission decides
whether to grant a special permit or
not.
>> Yep.
Okay, everybody's up to speed on that
and uh we'll wait for the special permit
application.
>> I've been waiting.
>> Okay. Yeah, as you said December
from the
So, just to be clear, he hasn't done
that for this
season. I'll call it yet for events.
Thank you.
>> Just giving you guys the heads up
cuz I'm sure we're going to be on
Facebook again.
Do we have a precedent how to deal with
this kind of thing?
>> It's it's a zoning violation. So, yeah.
I mean, it's
>> Yeah.
>> Yeah. It's it's as simple as they're
they're not authorized to do what
they're doing. That's a zoning
violation.
>> Okay. Notice a zoning violation. If it
continues, then then I guess it goes to
a cease and assist.
>> And this letter he sent was from May. So
he's he's had time to go live.
I remember that Facebook post that
wasn't that long ago.
Like I said, I'm not really in tune to
Facebook except I do use Facebook
Marketplace,
but other than that, not much.
A lot of these cars on Facebook
Marketplace from location. I haven't I
haven't you know mostly looking forward
to that
and then there there were several
others. There was a
correspondence
haven't gotten a reply yet. I talked to
him over the phone
hill silk fences down we put putting
single family residence there and
silence along the driveways down
promised me it would address that they
it would be addressed hasn't been
addressed so
check that
um
the
shel station on Route Six. The windows
were This is something Jen brought up to
me some time ago. The windows were you
can only cover 25% of the up to 25% of
your windows with advertisements and
stuff. That has been abaded.
>> That's what this packet was.
>> That's been abaded. And then
um
and then uh Benjamin Franklin
sent that letter. Mr. Benushi gave me a
call again. He assured me that he'd have
his engineer work on on
the necessary
modifications. uh and uh
come to the commission to modify the
special permit that was initially
issued to for that building and
property.
now that he has additional land to
>> go the other direction
>> spread out onto
and then uh remediate where he dug into
the embankment leure.
Okay,
that's all I got. Thank you.
>> Uh up next IWWC.
So we cancelled our most recent meeting
because it was on the same night as town
finger.
>> All right, final planner. John, you're
up.
>> Um, so not much in additional I
obviously had a number of conversations
this month with uh Peter Dali and
Lauren, the representatives of the the
developers. So just talking through the
process. um met yesterday with uh
economic development and looking forward
to helping move some of those priorities
forward. Um I also participated in the
first meeting of the regional uh
basically assembly of planners. Um
that's not a formal name but the capital
region council of governments um has
invited all of the regions uh town
planners to come and start talking about
the regional housing growth plans that
are we're going to have to start ramping
up um and kind of walk through the
process. Um there's nothing really to
report at this point other than um you
know the the
uh we are all kind of waiting for the
office of policy management OPM to
develop its um buildable land criteria
and its um big
uh big housing growth uh need numbers.
Both of those things aren't going to
happen until the fall. Um so it was
really just sort of an initial level
setting meeting um with the region's
planners and and we will obviously keep
you guys informed as as you know plans
and information progresses but but just
wanted you to know that I was
participating in a meeting on behalf of
and over for that. Um
uh I think
that's that's primarily it for me and
obviously I I I developed the draft of
the uh the proposed zoning rags but
we'll talk about that next month.
Thank you. Um,
and also I went through that state uh
the firm that state hired for the
housing analysis study.
>> Uh, that housing analysis study was is
is being superseded. The the the one
from Eco Northwest.
>> Yeah.
>> Yeah. That's that's sort of put to the
side. Uh, OPM is kind of re redoing it.
But I mean it's it's good that you
reviewed it, but that's Yeah,
>> I just got a big takeaway. I think I
brought it up in economic development
last night, but I wanted to just put it
on the record that one of the things
they did mention is besides the lack of
housing, we need better paying jobs. So,
I just wanted to throw that in there,
too, like just keep that in mind when
we're looking for development to get
more jobs, high paying jobs in town if
possible.
>> Sure.
>> It's my two cents anyway.
>> Um, well, I think that electro
>> Yes.
They're going to add some jobs.
>> Definitely.
>> Yeah.
>> Okay. Any public speak online? Nobody's
here.
>> I got one. Go ahead. If you haven't been
out to take a look at the playground and
the pickle ball courts and all that, you
ought to go see it. That is really
turning out nice.
>> Down the South.
>> Yeah.
>> I didn't know there pickle ball. That's
great. They've got four courts in there
and they got this big uh playcape thing
for the kids. Just uh a real nice
facility for the den. Excellent. That
was a good news story.
>> Thank you.
>> All right, moving on to approval of
minutes.
Make a motion to approve minutes for May
19th, 2026.
Second by
AJ. Okay. Thanks. Discussion.
>> No discussion but I will abstain as I
was not there.
>> Thank you.
>> Thanks.
>> Like they're good.
>> Yeah. Very good.
>> Yeah. Any other any other discussion?
>> Just Oh, I forgot not to do with the
minutes. Just a housekeeping thing. Um
Annay is still getting our emails.
>> Oh, I'm sorry. That'd be
>> It's probably just Yeah,
>> that' be my bad then. Yeah,
>> before it's no big deal. I saw her
somewhere and she didn't she didn't
mind. She just said, "Hey, I'm still
getting your emails." So,
>> yeah, I noticed that afternoon.
>> I I noticed that this afternoon. She was
on a couple of them.
>> All right.
All in favor of approval of minutes.
>> I
>> I am motion. Motion passes 401.
And
next meeting July 21st and uh Wayne or
we going to add just make sure you add
the uh
what uh John wants to talk about next
month
>> zoning revisions.
>> Oh the uh
>> the public act 251 zoning revisions.
>> Yeah 251 discussion. Yeah.
>> Thank you.
Are you gonna There's still going to be
in the discussion phase at that point,
right, John?
>> Um, yeah. I I mean, and yes. Um, you you
may want to you
uh wait, I don't know if we need to if
we to turn it into a formal application.
Do we need to fill out a we need to fill
out a form?
>> Yeah.
>> I I don't know if you just for
efficiency if you wanted this is
entirely up to you. I it it's totally
fine if we do sort of a discussion
presentation and you guys sort of say,
"All right, this is the direction we
want to go or you want to pick a
different direction." If it's the
direction you decide you want to go, you
could just turn it into an application
and and and schedule it for public
hearing the final the following month if
you wanted.
But
>> yeah, it's it's really up to you.
Sounds
>> good.
Last chance. Anything else?
Motion to all in favor. Second by Liam.
All in favor? I. I.
>> Thank you everybody.
>> Thanks everybody.